<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Local Government News Roundup</title>
	<atom:link href="https://lgnewsroundup.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://lgnewsroundup.com/</link>
	<description>Australia&#039;s No. 1 podcast for local government news and views</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 23:02:47 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.9</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://i0.wp.com/lgnewsroundup.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/03/cropped-Chris-Eddy-Tile-V.jpg?fit=32%2C32&#038;ssl=1</url>
	<title>Local Government News Roundup</title>
	<link>https://lgnewsroundup.com/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
<site xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">191119950</site>	<item>
		<title>Newsfeed &#8211; Tuesday, 9/12/25</title>
		<link>https://lgnewsroundup.com/newsfeed-tuesday-9-12-25/?utm_source=rss&#038;utm_medium=rss&#038;utm_campaign=newsfeed-tuesday-9-12-25</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[LG News Roundup]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 22:51:53 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[NSW]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Victoria]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://lgnewsroundup.com/?p=6743</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Geelong waterfront transformation plan vote dueGriffith Council to debate new dress codeSurf Coast seeks aquatic centre operatorCrackdown on authorised Bronte Beach party Greater Geelong&#160;councillors will vote tonight on a sweeping waterfront transformation plan featuring 32 projects across five precincts,&#160;according to the Geelong Advertiser. Key proposals include converting the northern end of Yarra Street into a [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://lgnewsroundup.com/newsfeed-tuesday-9-12-25/">Newsfeed &#8211; Tuesday, 9/12/25</a> appeared first on <a href="https://lgnewsroundup.com">Local Government News Roundup</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p class=""><a href="#geelong">Geelong waterfront transformation plan vote due</a><br><a href="#griffith">Griffith Council to debate new dress code</a><br><a href="#aquatic">Surf Coast seeks aquatic centre operator</a><br><a href="#waverley">Crackdown on authorised Bronte Beach party</a></p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<p id="geelong" class=""><strong>Greater Geelong</strong>&nbsp;councillors will vote tonight on a sweeping waterfront transformation plan featuring 32 projects across five precincts,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.heraldsun.com.au/news/geelong/geelong-council-set-to-endorse-sweeping-waterfront-transformation-plan/news-story/232696fa24f36ec6f1f97b787f8d950d">according to the Geelong Advertiser</a>.</p>



<p class="">Key proposals include converting the northern end of Yarra Street into a plaza-style setting and introducing a cultural walk highlighting Wadawurrung heritage.</p>



<p class="">The plan also includes upgrades to Poppy Kettle playground, development of Cunningham Pier, and expansion of the Western Beach maritime area.</p>



<p class="">Public consultation has reportedly confirmed strong community support for the staged upgrade.</p>



<p class="">The masterplan will guide council budgets and help secure external funding for the city&#8217;s waterfront precinct.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<p id="griffith" class=""><strong>Griffith City Council</strong>&nbsp;will debate a new dress code tonight requiring councillors to wear business casual attire to meetings.</p>



<p class=""><a href="https://regionriverina.com.au/flannel-or-formal-griffith-council-to-debate-dress-code-and-other-new-meeting-rules/113892/">Region Riverina reported the</a>&nbsp;proposed rule has put maverick councillor Mark Dal Bon&#8217;s preference for flannelette shirts in the spotlight.</p>



<p class="">Several residents have submitted objections, arguing the code could be discriminatory.</p>



<p class="">Another meeting rule proving controversial is the limiting of remote attendance via audio-visual link, but that has been mandated by the state government and cannot be changed.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<p id="aquatic" class=""><strong>Surf Coast Shire Council</strong>&nbsp;is seeking&nbsp;<a href="https://www.surfcoast.vic.gov.au/About-us/News-and-media/Council-to-engage-external-operator-to-manage-new-Wurdi-Baierr-Aquatic-and-Recreation-Centre">an external operator to manage the new Wurdi Baierr Aquatic and Recreation Centre,</a>&nbsp;opening in 2027.</p>



<p class="">The tender will open in mid-January, with the operator to being work at the end of 2026.</p>



<p class="">The Council will continue setting all fees and charges annually, while the operator manages day-to-day operations.</p>



<p class="">Construction of the centre is on track to finish by the end of 2026.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<p id="waverley" class=""><a href="https://www.smh.com.au/national/nsw/sydney-council-cracks-down-on-notorious-christmas-day-beach-bash-20251208-p5nlob.html">The Sydney Morning Herald has reported</a>&nbsp;on how&nbsp;<strong>Waverley Council</strong>&nbsp;is ramping up security at Bronte Beach this Christmas after 15,000 revellers left a trail of rubbish last year.</p>



<p class="">Police checkpoints will enforce alcohol and glass bans, while extra toilets, water stations and cleaning crews will be deployed throughout the day.</p>



<p class="">The unauthorised party has grown in popularity since the pandemic, sparking complaints about noise, anti-social behaviour and mess.</p>



<p class="">Residents say the beachfront park was turned into a &#8220;mass urinal&#8221; by partygoers.</p>



<p class="">Council says it can&#8217;t ban people from the beach but is committed to protecting community safety and amenity.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://lgnewsroundup.com/newsfeed-tuesday-9-12-25/">Newsfeed &#8211; Tuesday, 9/12/25</a> appeared first on <a href="https://lgnewsroundup.com">Local Government News Roundup</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<post-id xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">6743</post-id>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Levy backdown, mayor resigns, and a raffle debate &#8211; #526</title>
		<link>https://lgnewsroundup.com/levy-backdown-mayor-resigns-and-a-raffle-debate-526/?utm_source=rss&#038;utm_medium=rss&#038;utm_campaign=levy-backdown-mayor-resigns-and-a-raffle-debate-526</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[LG News Roundup]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 07 Dec 2025 20:34:18 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[New episode]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[CEO]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[International]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mayor]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Northern Territory]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[NSW]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[QLD]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[South Australia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tasmania]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Victoria]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Western Australia]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://lgnewsroundup.com/?p=6741</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Today on the Local Government News Roundup: The Local Government News Roundup is brought to you by the&#160;Victorian Local Governance Association, the national broadcaster on all things local government; with support from Symphony3 &#8211; simple, connected customer experiences. Listen to the episode here. Read along with all the news from this episode below: Victorian Report [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://lgnewsroundup.com/levy-backdown-mayor-resigns-and-a-raffle-debate-526/">Levy backdown, mayor resigns, and a raffle debate &#8211; #526</a> appeared first on <a href="https://lgnewsroundup.com">Local Government News Roundup</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p class="">Today on the Local Government News Roundup:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li class="">A government back down on the controversial Emergency Services levy</li>



<li class="">Alpine Shire’s mayor resigns after less than two weeks in the role</li>



<li class="">A rural NSW council commences a special rate variation process</li>



<li class="">Rowing clubs upset over a Sydney council’s swimming pool plan</li>



<li class="">Townsville&#8217;s new mayor wins his first political test</li>



<li class="">A Gold Coast councillor&#8217;s raffle ticket purchase on a corporate card sparks policy debate</li>



<li class="">Hobart council to shift focus to compliance after a new AFL stadium is approved</li>



<li class="">An infrastructure review reveals governance failures at a Tasmanian council</li>
</ul>



<p class="">The Local Government News Roundup is brought to you by the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.vlga.org.au/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Victorian Local Governance Association</a>, the national broadcaster on all things local government; with support from <a href="http://www.symphony3.com">Symphony3</a> &#8211; simple, connected customer experiences.</p>



<p class=""><a href="https://www.buzzsprout.com/1726495/episodes/18313594-levy-backdown-mayor-resigns-and-a-raffle-debate-526" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Listen to the episode here.</a></p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<p class="">Read along with all the news from this episode below:</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Victorian Report</h2>



<p class="">The Victorian Government has&nbsp;<a href="https://www.abc.net.au/news/2025-12-05/budget-update-victorian-government-jaclyn-symes-emergency-levy/106105012">backed down on controversial tax increases</a>&nbsp;for the Emergency Services Volunteers Fund.</p>



<p class="">Property owners faced steep rises, with some farmers looking at tens of thousands of dollars in extra charges.</p>



<p class="">The government will now delay increases for investment properties until July 2027 and freeze rates for farmers for two more years.</p>



<p class="">Treasurer Jaclyn Symes says the delay will give authorities time to get their processes right.</p>



<p class="">Councils have consistently advocated strongly about the impact of the levy, particularly on primary producers.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Greater Shepparton City Council</strong>&nbsp;was one of the first to respond to the news.</p>



<p class="">It&nbsp;<a href="https://greatershepparton.com.au/whats-happening/news/news-article/!/456/post/council-welcomes-further-relief-for-primary-producers-through-a-freeze-on-the-esvf">welcomed the decision</a>&nbsp;saying it would provide crucial relief to farmers and growers facing ongoing challenges.</p>



<p class="">Mayor Shane Sali said, &#8220;Although this is a win and a significant reprieve for many, we will continue the discussions and our ongoing advocacy”.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Rural Councils Victoria</strong>&nbsp;hailed the announcement&nbsp;<a href="https://www.linkedin.com/posts/rural-councils-victoria_we-did-it-after-months-of-sustained-advocacy-activity-7402593443212091392-8RsY">as a victory for its sustained advocacy</a>. While it welcomed the further delay, it said more changes are needed, and that it will keep fighting the levy until it is dead and buried.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-medium"><img data-recalc-dims="1" fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="300" height="200" src="https://i0.wp.com/lgnewsroundup.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/mayoralchangeover_image001_56310-jpg.webp?resize=300%2C200&#038;ssl=1" alt="" class="wp-image-6736" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/lgnewsroundup.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/mayoralchangeover_image001_56310-jpg.webp?resize=300%2C200&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/lgnewsroundup.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/mayoralchangeover_image001_56310-jpg.webp?resize=1024%2C683&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/lgnewsroundup.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/mayoralchangeover_image001_56310-jpg.webp?resize=768%2C512&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/lgnewsroundup.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/mayoralchangeover_image001_56310-jpg.webp?resize=1536%2C1024&amp;ssl=1 1536w, https://i0.wp.com/lgnewsroundup.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/mayoralchangeover_image001_56310-jpg.webp?w=2047&amp;ssl=1 2047w, https://i0.wp.com/lgnewsroundup.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/mayoralchangeover_image001_56310-jpg.webp?w=1280&amp;ssl=1 1280w, https://i0.wp.com/lgnewsroundup.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/mayoralchangeover_image001_56310-jpg.webp?w=1920&amp;ssl=1 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></figure>
</div>


<p class="">The mayor of&nbsp;<strong>Alpine Shire Council</strong>&nbsp;has&nbsp;<a href="https://www.alpineshire.vic.gov.au/news/resignation-mayor">resigned after less than 2 weeks</a>&nbsp;in the role.</p>



<p class="">Gareth Graham stepped down from the position on Friday and will remain as a councillor.</p>



<p class="">Deputy Mayor Cr Sarah Nicholas has assumed the responsibilities of mayor until the Council elects a new mayor.</p>



<p class="">No further information has been provided as to the reason for Cr Graham’s decision. CEO Will Jeremy said more details would be forthcoming regarding a mayoral election this week.</p>



<p class="">The State Government has applied an interim Erosion Management Overlay&nbsp;<a href="https://www.yarraranges.vic.gov.au/Our-Council/Latest-news/State-Government-to-apply-interim-Erosion-Management-Overlay">to high-risk landslip areas</a>&nbsp;across&nbsp;<strong>Yarra Ranges Shire</strong>. The move comes as Amendment C225, which proposes updated landslip mapping based on modern technology, undergoes independent review.</p>



<p class="">Current mapping dates back to the 1990s using aerial photography from the 1960s. The interim overlay will remain in place until October 2027 or until the amendment is finalised, ensuring developments in at-risk areas proceed safely.</p>



<p class="">A controversial proposal to build more than 1000 homes on the Cranbourne Golf Course will now be decided by&nbsp;<strong>Casey</strong>councillors in February.</p>



<p class=""><a href="https://cranbournenews.starcommunity.com.au/news/2025-12-03/cranbourne-golf-course-housing-plan-to-face-councillor-vote-in-february/">The Star reported that</a>&nbsp;Councillors have called in the planning application for 750 Glasscocks Road under land use planning protocols introduced after the IBAC Operation Sandon inquiry.</p>



<p class="">The application has received more than 50 formal objections from the community.</p>



<p class="">Casey Mayor Stefan Koomen says councillors believe the proposal is of significant interest due to its potential impact on local amenity, infrastructure and employment.</p>



<p class="">It will be the first major planning application to be decided by Casey&#8217;s newly elected councillors under the new protocols.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Hume City Council</strong>&nbsp;will explore ways to reduce growing rate arrears across the municipality, which have risen to 45.75 million dollars.</p>



<p class="">Councillor Kate Hamley put forward [a motion at the Council’s November meeting](file:///Users/chriseddy/Downloads/MINUTES-24-NOVEMBER-2025-OPEN.pdf), asking rates hardship be addressed, and that its financial hardship policy be reviewed.</p>



<p class="">Agreed actions include exploring incentives for payment plans and directly engaging with affected ratepayers to understand why they haven&#8217;t paid.</p>



<p class="">At tonight’s meeting, the Council will consider [formalising feedback on draft ministerial guidelines](file:///Users/chriseddy/Downloads/AGENDA-8-December-2025-Open.pdf) on the payment of rates and charges.</p>



<p class="">The&nbsp;<strong>City of Port Phillip</strong>&nbsp;<a href="https://www.portphillip.vic.gov.au/about-the-council/news-and-media/funding-boost-to-keep-port-phillip-moving-sustainably/">has welcomed news</a>&nbsp;that it will receive 1.5 million dollars per year to support active and sustainable transport initiatives.</p>



<p class="">The funding comes from the Victorian Government&#8217;s commitment to reinvest congestion levy revenue into affected communities.</p>



<p class="">Port Phillip&#8217;s share is part of a 15 million dollar annual investment secured through recent amendments to state taxation legislation.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Corangamite Shire Council</strong>&nbsp;has&nbsp;<a href="https://www.corangamite.vic.gov.au/Council/News-and-Media/Latest-News/Speed-cuts-to-improve-safety-on-residential-streets">announced new lower speed limits</a>&nbsp;for three suburban roads to improve community safety.</p>



<p class="">Bowen Street in Camperdown has dropped from 60 to 50 kilometres per hour, complementing new pedestrian outstands and traffic calming measures installed in April.</p>



<p class="">Baynes Street in Terang has also been reduced to 50 kilometres per hour following resident concerns about heavy truck traffic.</p>



<p class="">And Park Lane in Camperdown has been cut from 80 to 60 kilometres per hour due to increased pedestrian and cycling activity along a new concrete path.</p>



<p class="">All changes required approval from the Department of Transport following traffic assessments and community consultation.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Moira Shire Council</strong>&nbsp;has unveiled&nbsp;<a href="https://www.moira.vic.gov.au/Our-Council/News-and-information/Media-releases/A-10-year-plan-for-Moira's-urban-trees">a plan to increase urban tree canopy coverage</a>&nbsp;by 15 per cent over the next decade.</p>



<p class="">The council will plant 2400 additional trees on public land between 2025 and 2035, expanding on the existing 16,000 registered trees.</p>



<p class="">Council says appropriate consultation will be undertaken and there will be opportunities for community input in landscape planning and tree species selection.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Victorian Briefs</h2>



<p class="">The VEC has declared the result of a countback to fill a vacant position on&nbsp;<strong>Benalla Rural City Council.</strong></p>



<p class="">Vincent Michael Branigan will take the place of Nathan Tolliday, who resigned recently for work reasons.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Bass Coast Shire Council</strong>&nbsp;has secured 1.7 million dollars in federal funding&nbsp;<a href="https://www.basscoast.vic.gov.au/about-council/news-listing/federal-funding-secured-to-rebuild-stewart-road-bridge-in-kernot">to rebuild the Stewart Road Bridge in Kernot.</a></p>



<p class="">The Australian Government&#8217;s Safer Local Roads and Infrastructure Program will cover the bulk of the 2.2 million dollar project.</p>



<p class="">The bridge has been closed due to safety concerns after repeated overload impacts, forcing residents and emergency services to take lengthy detours.</p>



<p class="">The&nbsp;<strong>Rural City of Wangaratta</strong>&nbsp;has announced it will host Champions League Basketball&#8217;s 3X3 Australia event in January, featuring two days of basketball competition for all ages and skill levels.</p>



<p class="">The&nbsp;<a href="https://www.wangaratta.vic.gov.au/News-Articles/Wangaratta-secures-event-partnership-with-Champions-League-Basketball-3x3-Australia">event is Australia’s premiere 3X3 basketball even</a>t, combining elite sport with grassroots participation.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">NSW Report</h2>



<p class=""><strong>Muswellbrook Shire Council</strong>&nbsp;has launched&nbsp;<a href="https://www.muswellbrook.nsw.gov.au/council-opens-consultation-on-special-rate-variation-to-apply-only-mining-land-to-safeguard-muswellbrook-shires-future/">consultation on a Special Rate Variation targeting only mining land</a>&nbsp;to secure the region&#8217;s financial future.</p>



<p class="">The proposed 29 per cent increase would raise an additional six million dollars annually to protect essential services as local mines approach closure.</p>



<p class="">Residential rates will rise by 3.1 per cent, the lowest in the Hunter region.</p>



<p class="">Mining rate revenue is expected to drop by 25 per cent over the next decade due to mine closures, slashing five million dollars from Council&#8217;s annual income.</p>



<p class="">Local rowing clubs are upset about&nbsp;<strong>Inner West Council</strong>&nbsp;plans to build a three-point-eight million dollar swimming pool on Iron Cove in Sydney&#8217;s Parramatta River.</p>



<p class=""><a href="https://www.smh.com.au/national/nsw/this-sydney-council-wants-to-build-a-new-swimming-spot-rowers-are-up-in-arms-20251201-p5njvt.html">The Sydney Morning Herald reports</a>&nbsp;on concerns that the project threatens a historic two-thousand-metre rowing course that&#8217;s been in use since the eighteen-eighties.</p>



<p class="">More than one-thousand rowers from thirteen clubs and schools use the course for training and competitions.</p>



<p class="">The council has reduced the size of the pool in response to concerns, but rowers say safety and heritage issues remain unresolved.</p>



<p class="">The Inner West Local Planning Panel will consider the proposal on Tuesday.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Central Darling Shire Council</strong>&nbsp;has held its&nbsp;<a href="https://www.centraldarling.nsw.gov.au/files/assets/public/v/1/latest-news/2025/december-2025/media-release-historic-day-for-central-darling-first-council-meeting-under-new-model-final.pdf">first meeting under the new Rural and Remote Council model</a>, marking the end of more than ten years under administration.</p>



<p class="">New councillors were sworn into office on December 4th, with Councillor Daniel Fusi unanimously elected as Deputy Chair.</p>



<p class="">The council tackled a lengthy agenda including setting 2026 meeting dates, reviewing audited financial statements, and appointing consultants to develop the Community Strategic Plan.</p>



<p class="">The historic meeting signals a fresh start for the shire after years of administrative oversight.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Wagga Wagga City Council</strong>&nbsp;<a href="https://www.dailyadvertiser.com.au/story/9126967/wagga-council-call-on-michael-slater-honour-through-to-the-keeper/">has determined that it has no policy</a>&nbsp;to strip former cricketer Michael Slater of his Sporting Hall of Fame honour.</p>



<p class="">The Daily Advertiser reported that the debate has dragged on for 19 months, despite Cricket NSW recently removing Slater’s honours following domestic violence convictions.</p>



<p class="">A recent council workshop on renaming the former Michael Slater Oval ended without consensus, with no formal decision-making taking place.</p>



<p class="">The oval has been nameless since councillors voted to remove Slater&#8217;s name in May 2024.</p>



<p class="">Councillor Tim Koschel has resigned from&nbsp;<strong>Wagga Wagga City Council,</strong>&nbsp;<a href="https://news.wagga.nsw.gov.au/news-articles/2025/december-2025/summary-of-councils-1-december-2025-ordinary-meeting">effective from 31 January 2026.</a></p>



<p class="">The council has formally noted the resignation, and expressed appreciation to Cr Koschel for his dedicated service to the City , including his role as Chairperson of Riverina Water County Council and his contribution across three Council terms.</p>



<p class="">The process for filling the casual vacancy will be by the countback method, as previously resolved by the Council.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Lake Macquarie Council</strong>&nbsp;has appointed a recruitment consultant to advance its search for a new Chief Executive Officer, after the resignation of Morven Cameron in August.</p>



<p class="">Local Government Management Solutions will assist the council’s performance review panel, which has had a change &#8211; Councillor Michael Hannah has stepped away from the panel, replaced by Cr Kate Warner.</p>



<p class="">The council is [expected to ratify the next steps](file:///Users/chriseddy/Downloads/Agenda-Ordinary-Council-Meeting-8-December-2025-reduced-file-size.pdf) in the process at its meeting today.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">NSW Briefs:</h2>



<p class=""><strong>Cabonne Council</strong>&nbsp;has adopted&nbsp;<a href="https://cabonne.pulsesoftware.com/Pulse/Public.aspx?page=publicpolicies">a new Generative AI strategic policy</a>&nbsp;that enables staff to explore AI productivity tools while maintaining human oversight and protecting community data through safeguards like data de-identification and mandatory verification of AI outputs.</p>



<p class="">The policy explicitly prohibits&nbsp;<a href="https://www.forbesadvocate.com.au/news/council/ai-in-local-government-cabonne-sets-benefits-boundaries-in-policy-t7mofy32">the use of AI to make decisions</a>&nbsp;on behalf of council, keeping all decision-making authority with staff.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Orange City Council</strong>&nbsp;<a href="https://www.orange.nsw.gov.au/news/council-unwraps-free-parking-and-traffic-flow-trial-to-support-shopping-local-this-festive-season/">has introduced free parking</a>&nbsp;at the Ophir Car Park from December 3rd to Christmas Eve to support local businesses during the festive shopping rush.</p>



<p class="">Council is also trialling a portable traffic signal to ease congestion and help vehicles exit the city centre car park more smoothly.</p>



<p class="">If successful, similar measures could be rolled out for future busy periods like Easter.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Lismore City Council</strong>&nbsp;has&nbsp;<a href="https://www.lismore.nsw.gov.au/Council/Latest-news-and-updates/Latest-news/Staff-turned-recycling-into-Lismore%E2%80%99s-Christmas-gift">unveiled its 2025 Community Upcycled Christmas Tree</a>, marking a decade of staff building large-scale festive displays from recycled materials.</p>



<p class="">This year&#8217;s tree features more than 150 upcycled kerbside bin lids wrapped in fairy lights and decorated with recycled toys from the Revolve Shop.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Queensland Report</h2>



<p class=""><strong>Townsville</strong>&#8216;s new mayor Nick Dametto has won council approval for three adviser positions despite some lingering concerns following the previous mayor&#8217;s conduct.</p>



<p class="">Councillor Andrew Robinson warned he wouldn&#8217;t place blind trust in the new mayor but ultimately supported the motion,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.townsvillebulletin.com.au/news/townsville/new-mayor-nick-dametto-faces-first-test-in-vote-on-political-advisers/news-story/34274d7229036152787050ba3d346ceb">according to the Townsville Bulletin</a>.</p>



<p class="">The advisers will focus on legal and media, policy development, and business development.</p>



<p class="">Only Councillor Ann-Maree Greaney voted against, saying she&#8217;d support two advisers instead of three.</p>



<p class="">Former mayor Troy Thompson had his bid for three advisers rejected in 2024 after councillors said they didn&#8217;t trust his judgement.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Redland City Council</strong>&nbsp;will vote this week on whether to support LGAQ opposition to a proposed state law.</p>



<p class="">The bill would&nbsp;<a href="https://redlandbaysidenews.com.au/redland-council-to-weigh-in-on-proposed-law-forcing-councillors-out-if-they-run-for-state-parliament/">automatically remove councillors from office</a>&nbsp;if they nominate for Queensland Parliament.</p>



<p class="">Redland Bayside News reports that the LGAQ believes councillors should stay in their roles while campaigning, and a council report warns the change could trigger costly by-elections.</p>



<p class="">A December 17 deadline approaches for member councils to submit their votes.</p>



<p class="">A&nbsp;<strong>Gold Coast</strong>&nbsp;councillor&#8217;s use of her&nbsp;<a href="https://www.heraldsun.com.au/news/gold-coast/calls-for-change-after-councillor-wins-car-after-purchasing-ticket-on-council-credit-card/news-story/25ec85f80fbf90e027c8b4cacbc27e29?btr=7d22cdc05bdedc2b704e9e5e338aadf8">corporate credit card to buy a 350-dollar raffle ticket</a>&nbsp;has triggered a debate about expenditure policy.</p>



<p class="">Councillor Brooke Patterson won a 24,000-dollar car at a charity event. Mayor Tom Tate says the car will be donated back to charity, according to the Herald Sun.</p>



<p class="">There are now calls for a review to prevent councillors purchasing raffle tickets with council funds, with the matter will be decided at the next council meeting in January.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Noosa Council</strong>&nbsp;is moving to strengthen its role in reducing gambling-related harm.</p>



<p class="">Councillors have voted to explore&nbsp;<a href="https://www.noosa.qld.gov.au/About-Council/News-and-publications/Media-releases/2025/Council-moves-to-tighten-gaming-machine-use-on-community-land">a policy position on electronic gaming machines on council-owned and trustee land</a>.</p>



<p class="">Mayor Frank Wilkie says the aim is a clear framework for decisions about installing or expanding gaming machines on council land.</p>



<p class="">The council will also consider reinstating membership with the Alliance for Gambling Reform.</p>



<p class="">Toowoomba Regional Art Gallery will be closed until the New Year&nbsp;<a href="https://www.tr.qld.gov.au/about-council/news-publications/media-releases/16723-toowoomba-regional-art-gallery-closed-following-storm-damage-2">due to water damage from roof leaks</a>&nbsp;during heavy rainfall last month.</p>



<p class="">While the main gallery is closed for damage assessment and repairs, exhibitions and programs continue at the Crows Nest Gallery and Rosalie Gallery.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Toowoomba</strong>&nbsp;Cr Melissa Taylor said officers are assessing the full extent of the damage, and more information will be provided in due course.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Tasmania</h2>



<p class=""><strong>Hobart&#8217;s</strong>&nbsp;acting lord mayor says the council must respect parliament&#8217;s decision to approve the $1.13 billion Macquarie Point AFL stadium,&nbsp;<a href="https://pulsetasmania.com.au/news/precipice-of-massive-change-hobart-council-responds-to-stadium-approval/">according to Pulse Tasmania.</a></p>



<p class="">The council had formally opposed the project, citing heritage, environmental and planning concerns.</p>



<p class="">Acting Lord Mayor Zelinda Sherlock said the council’s focus will now shift to compliance and enforcement of planning conditions.</p>



<p class="">The 23,000-seat roofed venue will become home to the Tasmania Devils AFL team, with completion scheduled for 2029.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Kingborough Council</strong>&nbsp;has released independent reviews into two major infrastructure projects that ran months over schedule.</p>



<p class="">The Summerleas Road underpass and Kingston bus interchange both suffered significant delays due to governance failures and ignored expert advice.</p>



<p class="">The bus interchange sat finished but unusable for nearly 18 months because the design didn&#8217;t account for proper bus turning radius.</p>



<p class="">The road closure blew out from eight weeks to 20 due to utility issues and environmental surveys done reactively.</p>



<p class="">Mayor Paula Wriedt said the council has already begun implementing 11 recommendations to strengthen future project delivery,&nbsp;<a href="https://pulsetasmania.com.au/news/kingborough-council-releases-reviews-into-delayed-infrastructure-projects/">according to Pulse Tasmania.</a></p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">South Australia</h2>



<p class="">The&nbsp;<strong>Local Government Association of South Australia</strong>&nbsp;is calling for&nbsp;<a href="https://www.lga.sa.gov.au/news-and-events/news/latest-news/2025/nominate-for-the-ceo-advisory-group">nominations from regional CEOs to join its Advisory Group.</a></p>



<p class="">A vacancy has opened following the resignation of Bridget Mather from&nbsp;<strong>Coorong District Counci</strong>l.</p>



<p class="">The successful candidate will attend at least four meetings annually starting February 1st.</p>



<p class="">It is a voluntary position with no payment offered. Applications close January 9th.</p>



<p class="">The South Australian Premier and Cabinet ministers will be in&nbsp;<strong>Adelaide Hills</strong>&nbsp;for&nbsp;<a href="https://www.ahc.sa.gov.au/community/latest-news/join-premier-peter-malinauskas-and-government-ministers-for-community-cabinet-at-heathfield-high-school-on-december-9">a Community Cabinet meeting tomorrow</a>, December 9.</p>



<p class="">The council has encouraged community members to register to attend and ask questions at the forum, which follows a community bbq at 4.30pm.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Western Australia</h2>



<p class="">Western Australia is&nbsp;<a href="https://www-dlgsc-wa-gov-au.cdn.ampproject.org/c/s/www.dlgsc.wa.gov.au/amp/2025/12/03/expression-of-interest-panel-of-monitors/djdyMHpURm9nWm4zTVZkcmVKbXp3Q2xodXR3PQ2">establishing a Panel of Monitors</a>&nbsp;to support local governments and prevent dysfunction from January 2026.</p>



<p class="">The Local Government Inspector will appoint monitors to work with councils facing performance issues or compliance challenges.</p>



<p class="">Monitors will observe meetings, review practices, and help resolve issues collaboratively—but they won&#8217;t act as investigators.</p>



<p class="">Ideal candidates need expertise in governance, finance, conflict resolution, or stakeholder engagement.</p>



<p class="">Applications from aspiring monitors close 4pm Wednesday, December 17th, 2025.</p>



<p class="">An illegal multi-day music festival in the Carbunup area has been shut down before it started.</p>



<p class=""><strong>City of Busselton</strong>&nbsp;staff teamed up with WA Police and conservation authorities&nbsp;<a href="https://www.busselton.wa.gov.au/news/illegal-multi-day-music-festival-forced-to-cancel-due-to-lack-of-approvals/974?c=17">to cancel the event</a>&nbsp;after the organiser failed to obtain any required approvals including risk management plans, bushfire plans, or liquor licenses.</p>



<p class="">Mayor Phill Cronin said drone surveillance is being used to monitor for similar illegal activities across the region.</p>



<p class="">The&nbsp;<strong>City of Fremantl</strong>e&#8217;s newly-built changeroom facilities at South Beach&nbsp;<a href="https://www.fremantle.wa.gov.au/your-city-and-council/news-and-media/vandals-target-south-beach-changerooms/">have been repeatedly vandalised over recent weeks</a>, prompting swift repairs and increased security patrols.</p>



<p class="">The City is reviewing CCTV footage and has deployed community safety officers to monitor the area more closely.</p>



<p class="">Residents are being urged to report any vandalism or antisocial behaviour to Crimestoppers to help protect the public amenities.</p>



<p class="">NT:</p>



<p class="">E-scooters and bikes are back online in&nbsp;<strong>Darwin</strong>, after they were removed before Cyclone Fina hit the region recently.</p>



<p class="">And the council has now&nbsp;<a href="https://www.darwin.nt.gov.au/council/news-media/beam-back-online-for-darwin-residents-keeping-the-city-connected">extended Beam&#8217;s contract for another two years</a>&nbsp;until December 2027.</p>



<p class="">Since launching in December 2023, the service has clocked up nearly 950,000 trips and over one million kilometers.</p>



<p class="">New Apollo Lite e-bikes designed for easier riding will soon join the Darwin fleet.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Global Report</h2>



<p class="">UK:</p>



<p class="">Reform UK has&nbsp;<a href="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/2025/dec/05/reform-uk-revokes-membership-ian-cooper-council-leader-accused-of-racism">revoked the membership of Ian Cooper</a>, leader of&nbsp;<strong>Staffordshire County Council,</strong>&nbsp;following allegations of racist online abuse.</p>



<p class="">The Guardian reported that Cooper allegedly called London Mayor Sadiq Khan a &#8220;narcissistic Pakistani&#8221; and said Justice Secretary David Lammy should not be allowed in parliament as a first-generation migrant.</p>



<p class="">The party said Cooper failed to declare social media accounts during candidate vetting.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Cambridge City Council</strong>&nbsp;has admitted making an error after claiming it removed &#8220;underused&#8221; public bins in the historic city,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/c4gk7ze8k7mo">according to a report from BBC News.</a></p>



<p class="">The council now says no underused bins have been removed to date, contradicting its August statement about a trial to ensure bins were in the right place.</p>



<p class="">The authority also made a second mistake in a Freedom of Information response, incorrectly stating that zero waste was recycled from city centre bins.</p>



<p class="">council has apologised for the errors and says it&#8217;s working to improve internal checks.</p>



<p class="">The Northern Ireland Local Government Commissioner has cleared the mayor of&nbsp;<a href="https://www.northernirelandworld.com/news/politics/council/mayor-of-lisburn-and-castlereagh-cleared-of-any-misconduct-by-watchdog-5431772">Lisburn and Castlereagh</a>&nbsp;Amanda Grehan&nbsp;<a href="https://www.northernirelandworld.com/news/politics/council/mayor-of-lisburn-and-castlereagh-cleared-of-any-misconduct-by-watchdog-5431772">of any conduct breaches following a complaint.</a></p>



<p class="">The allegation stemmed from an October council vote on &#8220;innocent victims&#8221; of the Troubles, where Grehan cast the deciding vote along party lines.</p>



<p class="">The commissioner concluded there was no evidence of code of conduct violations. Some councillors have condemned the complaint as politically motivated and vexatious.</p>



<p class="">USA:</p>



<p class="">The Mayor of&nbsp;<strong>Bogalusa</strong>, Louisiana, Tyrin Truong has pleaded not guilty to charges of malfeasance, public intimidation, and theft,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.wdsu.com/article/louisiana-bogalusa-mayor-tyrin-truong-not-guilty-plea/69597783">according to WDSU News.</a></p>



<p class="">The 26-year-old mayor was indicted following his January arrest in connection with a drug and prostitution investigation.</p>



<p class="">State police linked the operation to dangerous controlled substances including opioids and MDMA.</p>



<p class="">Six others were arrested in the investigation, which began when authorities learned of a drug trafficking organisation in Bogalusa.</p>



<p class="">Mr Truong&#8217;s next court hearing is scheduled for January 14th.</p>



<p class=""><strong>New York City Council</strong>&nbsp;announced on Friday that had&nbsp;<a href="https://council.nyc.gov/press/2025/12/04/3014/">overridden mayoral vetoes on four bills.</a></p>



<p class="">One measure caps rent contributions for voucher holders at 30 percent of monthly income, blocking proposed increases to 40 percent.</p>



<p class="">Two bills require large employers to report pay data and mandate annual pay equity studies to address gender and racial disparities.</p>



<p class="">The Council also passed legislation requiring quarterly payments to nonprofits with city contracts to address chronic late payment issues.</p>



<p class="">Additional measures passed by the Council include water safety programs, mental health training for construction workers, and the establishment of a permanent Office of the Census.</p>



<p class="">CANADA:</p>



<p class=""><strong>Edmonton</strong>&nbsp;city councillors have locked in a 6.9 per cent property tax increase for 2026, higher than the originally planned 6.4 per cent.</p>



<p class="">The rate jumped after council approved 11 million dollars for the city&#8217;s tourism body, Explore Edmonton.</p>



<p class=""><a href="https://www.ctvnews.ca/edmonton/article/city-council-locks-in-on-69-property-tax-hike/">CTV news reported that</a>&nbsp;the average homeowner will pay an extra 245 dollars in taxes next year.</p>



<p class="">The&nbsp;<strong>City of Vancouver</strong>&nbsp;has laid off approximately 30 non-unionised staff members&nbsp;<a href="https://www.ctvnews.ca/vancouver/article/city-of-vancouver-lays-off-dozens-of-staff-following-property-tax-freeze/">following a decision to freeze property taxes next year.</a></p>



<p class="">The cuts are part of Mayor Ken Sim&#8217;s &#8220;Zero Means Zero&#8221; initiative to find 120 million dollars in savings.</p>



<p class="">City leadership is reviewing structures and staffing, with additional changes expected in early 2026.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://lgnewsroundup.com/levy-backdown-mayor-resigns-and-a-raffle-debate-526/">Levy backdown, mayor resigns, and a raffle debate &#8211; #526</a> appeared first on <a href="https://lgnewsroundup.com">Local Government News Roundup</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<post-id xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">6741</post-id>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>VIC: Alpine Shire Mayor resigns</title>
		<link>https://lgnewsroundup.com/vic-alpine-shire-mayor-resigns/?utm_source=rss&#038;utm_medium=rss&#038;utm_campaign=vic-alpine-shire-mayor-resigns</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[LG News Roundup]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 06 Dec 2025 00:52:51 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Victoria]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://lgnewsroundup.com/?p=6735</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The mayor of&#160;Alpine Shire Council&#160;has&#160;resigned after less than 2 weeks&#160;in the role. Gareth Graham stepped down from the position on Friday and will remain as a councillor. Deputy Mayor Cr Sarah Nicholas has assumed the responsibilities of mayor until the Council elects a new mayor. No further information has been provided as to the reason [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://lgnewsroundup.com/vic-alpine-shire-mayor-resigns/">VIC: Alpine Shire Mayor resigns</a> appeared first on <a href="https://lgnewsroundup.com">Local Government News Roundup</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p class="">The mayor of&nbsp;<strong>Alpine Shire Council</strong>&nbsp;has&nbsp;<a href="https://www.alpineshire.vic.gov.au/news/resignation-mayor">resigned after less than 2 weeks</a>&nbsp;in the role.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-medium"><img data-recalc-dims="1" decoding="async" width="300" height="200" src="https://i0.wp.com/lgnewsroundup.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/mayoralchangeover_image001_56310-jpg.webp?resize=300%2C200&#038;ssl=1" alt="" class="wp-image-6736" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/lgnewsroundup.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/mayoralchangeover_image001_56310-jpg.webp?resize=300%2C200&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/lgnewsroundup.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/mayoralchangeover_image001_56310-jpg.webp?resize=1024%2C683&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/lgnewsroundup.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/mayoralchangeover_image001_56310-jpg.webp?resize=768%2C512&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/lgnewsroundup.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/mayoralchangeover_image001_56310-jpg.webp?resize=1536%2C1024&amp;ssl=1 1536w, https://i0.wp.com/lgnewsroundup.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/mayoralchangeover_image001_56310-jpg.webp?w=2047&amp;ssl=1 2047w, https://i0.wp.com/lgnewsroundup.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/mayoralchangeover_image001_56310-jpg.webp?w=1280&amp;ssl=1 1280w, https://i0.wp.com/lgnewsroundup.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/mayoralchangeover_image001_56310-jpg.webp?w=1920&amp;ssl=1 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></figure>
</div>


<p class="">Gareth Graham stepped down from the position on Friday and will remain as a councillor.</p>



<p class="">Deputy Mayor Cr Sarah Nicholas has assumed the responsibilities of mayor until the Council elects a new mayor.</p>



<p class="">No further information has been provided as to the reason for Cr Graham’s decision. CEO Will Jeremy said more details would be forthcoming regarding a mayoral election next week.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://lgnewsroundup.com/vic-alpine-shire-mayor-resigns/">VIC: Alpine Shire Mayor resigns</a> appeared first on <a href="https://lgnewsroundup.com">Local Government News Roundup</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<post-id xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">6735</post-id>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Newsfeed &#8211; Friday, 5/12/25</title>
		<link>https://lgnewsroundup.com/newsfeed-friday-5-12-25/?utm_source=rss&#038;utm_medium=rss&#038;utm_campaign=newsfeed-friday-5-12-25</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[LG News Roundup]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:10:19 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[NSW]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[QLD]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[South Australia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Victoria]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Western Australia]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://lgnewsroundup.com/?p=6724</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>ESVF freeze decision welcomedFirst test for Townsville&#8217;s new mayor at special council meeting todaySA Regional CEOs invited to nominate for advisory boardWA panel of local government monitors &#8211; applications openToowoomba closes gallery due to storm damageNew councillor for Benalla Rural City CouncilSpecial rate variation proposed for Muswellbrook mining landMoreton Bay Anzac memorial centenary celebrations this [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://lgnewsroundup.com/newsfeed-friday-5-12-25/">Newsfeed &#8211; Friday, 5/12/25</a> appeared first on <a href="https://lgnewsroundup.com">Local Government News Roundup</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p class=""><a href="#esv">ESVF freeze decision welcomed</a><br><a href="#dametto">First test for Townsville&#8217;s new mayor at special council meeting today</a><br><a href="#lgasa">SA Regional CEOs invited to nominate for advisory board</a><br><a href="#monitors">WA panel of local government monitors &#8211; applications open</a><br><a href="#toowoomba">Toowoomba closes gallery due to storm damage</a><br><a href="#benalla">New councillor for Benalla Rural City Council</a><br><a href="#muswellbrook">Special rate variation proposed for Muswellbrook mining land</a><br><a href="#moreton-bay">Moreton Bay Anzac memorial centenary celebrations this weekend</a></p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<p id="esv" class="">VIC: The Victorian Government has&nbsp;<a href="https://www.abc.net.au/news/2025-12-05/budget-update-victorian-government-jaclyn-symes-emergency-levy/106105012">backed down on controversial tax increases</a>&nbsp;for the Emergency Services and Volunteers Fund.</p>



<p class="">Property owners faced steep rises, with some farmers looking at tens of thousands of dollars in extra charges.</p>



<p class="">The government will now delay increases for investment properties until July 2027 and freeze rates for farmers for two more years.</p>



<p class="">Treasurer Jaclyn Symes says the delay will give authorities time to get their processes right.</p>



<p class="">Councils have consistently advocated strongly about the impact of the levy, particularly on primary producers.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Greater Shepparton City Council</strong>&nbsp;was one of the first to respond to today’s news.</p>



<p class="">It&nbsp;<a href="https://greatershepparton.com.au/whats-happening/news/news-article/!/456/post/council-welcomes-further-relief-for-primary-producers-through-a-freeze-on-the-esvf">welcomed the decision</a>&nbsp;saying it would provided crucial relief to farmers and growers facing ongoing challenges.</p>



<p class="">Mayor Shane Sali said, &#8220;Although this is a win and a significant reprieve for many, we will continue the discussions and our ongoing advocacy”.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<p id="dametto" class="">QLD: New&nbsp;<strong>Townsville</strong>&nbsp;Mayor Nick Dametto is seeking council approval for three political advisers in a special meeting today.</p>



<p class="">Mayors are entitled to three advisers under the Local Government Act to handle strategic issues and community engagement.</p>



<p class=""><a href="https://www.couriermail.com.au/news/townsville/new-mayor-nick-dametto-faces-first-test-in-vote-on-political-advisers/news-story/34274d7229036152787050ba3d346ceb">The Courier Mail reports that</a>&nbsp;former mayor Troy Thompson had a similar bid rejected in 2024 after councillors said they didn&#8217;t trust his judgment.</p>



<p class="">The vote marks Dametto&#8217;s first major test since taking office.</p>



<p class="">The meeting will also address appointments to various city committees and organisations.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<p id="lgasa" class="">SA: The&nbsp;<strong>Local Government Association of South Australia</strong>&nbsp;is calling for&nbsp;<a href="https://www.lga.sa.gov.au/news-and-events/news/latest-news/2025/nominate-for-the-ceo-advisory-group">nominations from regional CEOs to join its Advisory Group.</a></p>



<p class="">A vacancy has opened following the resignation of Bridget Mather from&nbsp;<strong>Coorong District Counci</strong>l.</p>



<p class="">The successful candidate will attend at least four meetings annually starting February 1st.</p>



<p class="">It is a voluntary position with no payment offered. Applications close January 9th.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<p id="monitors" class="">WA: Western Australia is&nbsp;<a href="https://www-dlgsc-wa-gov-au.cdn.ampproject.org/c/s/www.dlgsc.wa.gov.au/amp/2025/12/03/expression-of-interest-panel-of-monitors/djdyMHpURm9nWm4zTVZkcmVKbXp3Q2xodXR3PQ2">establishing a Panel of Monitors</a>&nbsp;to support local governments and prevent dysfunction from January 2026.</p>



<p class="">The Local Government Inspector will appoint monitors to work with councils facing performance issues or compliance challenges.</p>



<p class="">Monitors will observe meetings, review practices, and help resolve issues collaboratively—but they won&#8217;t act as investigators.</p>



<p class="">Ideal candidates need expertise in governance, finance, conflict resolution, or stakeholder engagement.</p>



<p class="">Applications from aspiring monitors close 4pm Wednesday, December 17th, 2025.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<p id="toowoomba" class="">QLD: Toowoomba Regional Art Gallery will be closed until the New Year&nbsp;<a href="https://www.tr.qld.gov.au/about-council/news-publications/media-releases/16723-toowoomba-regional-art-gallery-closed-following-storm-damage-2">due to water damage from roof leaks</a>&nbsp;during heavy rainfall last month.</p>



<p class="">While the main gallery is closed for damage assessment and repairs, exhibitions and programs continue at the Crows Nest Gallery and Rosalie Gallery.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Toowoomba</strong>&nbsp;Cr Melissa Taylor said offers are assessing the full extent of the damage, and more information will be provided in due course.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<p id="benalla" class="">VIC: The VEC has declared the result of a countback to fill a vacant position on&nbsp;<strong>Benalla Rural City Council.</strong></p>



<p class="">Vincent Michael Branigan will take the place of Nathan Tolliday, who resigned recently for work reasons.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<p id="muswellbrook" class="">NSW: <strong>Muswellbrook Shire Council</strong>&nbsp;has launched&nbsp;<a href="https://www.muswellbrook.nsw.gov.au/council-opens-consultation-on-special-rate-variation-to-apply-only-mining-land-to-safeguard-muswellbrook-shires-future/">consultation on a Special Rate Variation targeting only mining land</a>&nbsp;to secure the region&#8217;s financial future.</p>



<p class="">The proposed 29 per cent increase would raise an additional six million dollars annually to protect essential services as local mines approach closure.</p>



<p class="">Residential rates will rise by 3.1 per cent, the lowest in the Hunter region.</p>



<p class="">Mining rate revenue is expected to drop by 25 per cent over the next decade due to mine closures, slashing five million dollars from Council&#8217;s annual income.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<p id="moreton-bay" class="">QLD: The&nbsp;<strong>City of Moreton Bay</strong>&nbsp;is&nbsp;<a href="https://www.moretonbay.qld.gov.au/News/Media/Avenue%E2%80%99s-powerful-tribute-to-fallen-celebrated-a-century-on">celebrating the centenary of Anzac Memorial Avenue</a>&nbsp;this weekend.</p>



<p class="">The historic road between Petrie and Redcliffe was officially opened on December 5, 1925, honouring fallen soldiers from World War One.</p>



<p class="">Originally proposed by Thomas Rothwell in 1921, the project attracted enormous community support, raising 7,000 pounds locally with another 12,000 from governments.</p>



<p class="">Some 1,700 trees were planted along the avenue, each representing a fallen hero. Today, it remains a vital piece of infrastructure and a living memorial to Queensland&#8217;s servicemen.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>
<p>The post <a href="https://lgnewsroundup.com/newsfeed-friday-5-12-25/">Newsfeed &#8211; Friday, 5/12/25</a> appeared first on <a href="https://lgnewsroundup.com">Local Government News Roundup</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<post-id xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">6724</post-id>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>&#8220;Subverting democracy&#8221;, councillors suspended and accosted &#8211; #525</title>
		<link>https://lgnewsroundup.com/subverting-democracy-councillors-suspended-and-accosted-525/?utm_source=rss&#038;utm_medium=rss&#038;utm_campaign=subverting-democracy-councillors-suspended-and-accosted-525</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[LG News Roundup]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 20:22:26 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[New episode]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[International]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[NSW]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[QLD]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[South Australia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tasmania]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Victoria]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Western Australia]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://lgnewsroundup.com/?p=6722</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>In this edition of the Local Government News Roundup: All of that and more just ahead on Australia’s number one local government podcast. Plus we go live to Las Vegas in the states where Fergal Coleman from Symphony3 is at the AWS reInvent conference getting the lowdown of where AI technology is taking us in [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://lgnewsroundup.com/subverting-democracy-councillors-suspended-and-accosted-525/">&#8220;Subverting democracy&#8221;, councillors suspended and accosted &#8211; #525</a> appeared first on <a href="https://lgnewsroundup.com">Local Government News Roundup</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p class="">In this edition of the Local Government News Roundup:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li class="">A Merri-bek councillor to be suspended for misconduct</li>



<li class="">A councillor accosted in public over a controversial pool decision</li>



<li class="">The NSW Council set to fly the Palestinian flag</li>



<li class="">Environmental vandalism under investigation by Noosa Council</li>



<li class="">A Queensland council’s calls for help with a recent crime spike</li>



<li class="">A South Australian mayor resigns, effective immediately</li>



<li class="">and Perth’s Lord Mayor abandons a controversial workplace culture review</li>
</ul>



<p class="">All of that and more just ahead on Australia’s number one local government podcast.</p>



<p class="">Plus we go live to Las Vegas in the states where Fergal Coleman from Symphony3 is at the AWS reInvent conference getting the lowdown of where AI technology is taking us in the very near future.</p>



<p class="">The Local Government News Roundup is brought to you by the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.vlga.org.au/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Victorian Local Governance Association</a>, the national broadcaster on all things local government; with support from <a href="http://www.symphony3.com">Symphony3</a> &#8211; simple, connected customer experiences.</p>



<p class=""><a href="https://www.buzzsprout.com/1726495/episodes/18300993-subverting-democracy-councillors-suspended-and-accosted-525" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Listen to the episode here.</a></p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<p class="">Read along with all the news from this episode below:</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Victorian Report</h2>



<p class=""><strong>Merri-bek</strong>&nbsp;Councillor Adam Pulford will be suspended for 14 days after&nbsp;<a href="https://www.merri-bek.vic.gov.au/globalassets/website-merri-bek/areas/my-council/council-and-committee-meetings/council-and-parm-meetings/agendas/2025-agenda/council-agenda-10-december-2025---pdf-with-attachments.pdf">an arbiter make a finding of misconduct</a>&nbsp;for breaches of three of the standards of conduct in the Model Councillor Code Of Conduct.</p>



<p class="">A complaint was made by Cr Oscar Yildiz, alleging that the breaches occurred during debate on an agenda item about rainbow crossings.</p>



<p class="">Cr Yildiz alleged that Cr Pulford’s comments during debate personalised rather than engaged respectfully on the issue.</p>



<p class="">Cr Pulford was criticised for his use of the word &#8220;duplicitousness&#8221; and failing to pause sufficiently during debate.</p>



<p class="">Arbiter Matthew Evans found that Cr Pulford did not treat Cr Yildiz with dignity, fairness, objectivity, courtesy and respect; and that his demeanour and lack of restraint in his personal remarks likely diminished public trust and confidence in the council.</p>



<p class="">The Arbiter considered Cr Pulford’s partial apology for the hurt caused and full cooperation with the Arbitration process in determining a 14 day period of suspension.</p>



<p class="">He chose not to impose the requirement for an apology, considering that the outcome of the process should be “corrective not performative.”</p>



<p class="">The suspension will take effect next week after the Arbiter’s report is tabled at the Council’s December 10th meeting.</p>



<p class="">A&nbsp;<strong>Moyne Shire</strong>&nbsp;councillor has been verbally abused and given the middle finger over the decision to close Port Fairy&#8217;s Belfast Aquatics pool.</p>



<p class="">The Standard reported that Councillor Karen Foster was accosted at a service station on Saturday morning by an angry resident.</p>



<p class="">The incident follows council&#8217;s announcement that two million dollars worth of repairs are needed at the facility.</p>



<p class="">A petition to save the pool has attracted more than fifteen hundred signatures.</p>



<p class="">Councillor Foster, a former mayor of the shire, is calling for respectful debate despite community anger over the closure.</p>



<p class="">Source:&nbsp;<em>The Standard (Warrnambool, Australia), December 4, 2025</em></p>



<p class="">The Department of Health has confirmed the first detection of Japanese encephalitis virus in mosquitoes for the 2025-26 season in the Horsham area.</p>



<p class="">The virus was found in mosquito traps as part of Victoria&#8217;s Arbovirus Disease Control Program.</p>



<p class=""><a href="https://www.yarriambiack.vic.gov.au/Home/Tabs/News/Japanese-Encephalitis-virus-detected">Yarriambiack Shire</a>&nbsp;and&nbsp;<a href="https://www.hrcc.vic.gov.au/Our-Council/News-and-Media/Latest-News/Horsham-Rural-City-Council-Responds-to-Japanese-Encephalitis-Virus-Detection">Horsham Rural City Council</a>&nbsp;have issued alerts to residents to protect themselves by wearing long clothing, using repellent and removing stagnant water around homes.</p>



<p class="">Vaccinations are available for locals over two months old from local pharmacies and health centres.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Warrnambool City Council</strong>&nbsp;has missed out on one million dollars in state government funding for the Friendly Societies Park oval upgrade.</p>



<p class="">The council will now tip in an extra three hundred and fifty thousand dollars to keep the one point seven three million dollar project alive.</p>



<p class="">South Warrnambool Football Netball Club has also increased its contribution to two hundred thousand dollars.</p>



<p class="">Source:&nbsp;<em>The Standard (Warrnambool, Australia), December 4, 2025</em></p>



<p class=""><strong>Warrnambool City Council</strong>&#8216;s infrastructure and environment director David Leahy is leaving after five years in the role.</p>



<p class="">Mr Leahy, a former chief executive of West Wimmera Shire, oversaw some of Warrnambool’s biggest projects of the past decade including the library, Reid Oval and the new boat ramp.</p>



<p class="">He plans to stay in Warrnambool and pick up short-<em>term work rather than fully retire, according to the Standard.</em>&nbsp;(4th December 2025)</p>



<p class=""><strong>Murrindindi Shire Council</strong>&nbsp;has released draft&nbsp;<a href="https://www.murrindindi.vic.gov.au/Council/News-and-Media/Council-News/Murrindindi-Shire-leads-the-way-with-draft-guidelines-for-renewable-energy-development">guidelines for renewable energy development</a>, open for community feedback until February 8, 2026.</p>



<p class="">The guidelines respond to growing concern about large-scale energy projects and their impact on farming, tourism, and the local landscape.</p>



<p class="">Deputy Mayor Anita Carr says the framework puts community values first, demanding genuine engagement, transparency, and tangible local benefits from developers.</p>



<p class="">The guidelines emphasise protection of significant landscapes, partnership with Traditional Owners, and clear criteria for project siting and decommissioning.</p>



<p class="">Council is urging all residents to review the draft and share their views on The Loop, their online engagement platform.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Frankston City Council</strong>&nbsp;is investing $10 million into&nbsp;<a href="https://www.frankston.vic.gov.au/Council/News-and-media/Latest-News/Media-Release-2025/60m-to-Transform-Nepean-Highway-and-Renew-Frankston%E2%80%99s-City-Centre">the transformation of Nepean Highway</a>, joining the Federal Government&#8217;s $50 million election commitment for a total $60 million project.</p>



<p class="">The revitalisation will turn the highway into a safe, people-focused boulevard with improved connections between the city centre and waterfront.</p>



<p class="">Planned upgrades include safer pedestrian crossings, cycling paths, street trees, and traffic calming measures along the entire corridor.</p>



<p class="">Mayor Kris Bolam says the investment will encourage visitors to stop in Frankston rather than simply drive through.</p>



<p class="">After nearly 10 years of planning and three years of construction, Omeo Mountain Bike Park&nbsp;<a href="https://www.eastgippsland.vic.gov.au/media-releases/omeo-mtb-park-update-december-2025">officially opens this Friday</a>&nbsp;with 114 kilometres of world-class trails.</p>



<p class="">The network in&nbsp;<strong>East Gippsland Shire</strong>&nbsp;includes trails for every skill level from family-friendly green trails to double-black gravity descents with up to 590 metres of vertical drop.</p>



<p class="">The opening weekend features official ceremonies, shuttle rides, live music and a film premiere.</p>



<p class="">The park has created around 30 full-time jobs during construction and is set to transform Omeo into one of Australia&#8217;s premier mountain biking destinations.</p>



<p class=""><strong>City of Port Phillip</strong>&nbsp;has welcomed a 12 million dollar Victorian Liberal Party&nbsp;<a href="https://www.portphillip.vic.gov.au/about-the-council/news-and-media/council-welcomes-12-million-commitment-for-st-kilda-primary-school-community-facility/">election commitment for a new school hall</a>&nbsp;at St Kilda Primary School.</p>



<p class="">The commitment was announced by Member for Prahran Rachel Westaway and would fund a multi-purpose indoor hall and performing arts space.</p>



<p class="">The facility will support school assemblies, performances and sporting activities while creating opportunities for local events and community programs.</p>



<p class="">Council praised St Kilda Primary School&#8217;s vigorous advocacy campaign for the project.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Victorian Briefs</h2>



<p class="">The&nbsp;<strong>City of Casey</strong>&nbsp;is proposing to&nbsp;<a href="https://www.casey.vic.gov.au/news/rezoning-proposal-support-cranbourne%E2%80%99s-growth">rezone two parcels of farming land in Cranbourne</a>&nbsp;for residential development to meet growing housing demand near the town centre.</p>



<p class="">An environmental assessment confirms the land is suitable for homes, despite being near two former landfill sites.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Warrnambool</strong>&#8216;s&nbsp;<a href="https://www.warrnambool.vic.gov.au/citys-first-pump-track-now-open">first pump track is now ope</a>n, funded by a $150,000 Australian Government grant as part of the Council&#8217;s efforts to enhance active recreation along the Merri River corridor.</p>



<p class="">Mayor Ben Blain said he expected the facility to be an instant hit, as it opens just in time for summer.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Latrobe City Council</strong>&nbsp;has&nbsp;<a href="https://www.latrobe.vic.gov.au/news-and-media/More_major_events_to_take_place_in_Latrobe_City">endorsed funding for three major events</a>&nbsp;with a combined economic impact of more than six-point-five million dollars.</p>



<p class="">The events include the 2026 Motorcycling Australia ProMX, the 2027 Football Victoria Country Championships and a five-year agreement for the Traralgon Junior International Tennis Championships from 2027 to 2031.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">NSW Report</h2>



<p class=""><strong>Wollongong City Council</strong>&nbsp;will&nbsp;<a href="https://wollongong.nsw.gov.au/news/wollongong-city-council-to-raise-palestinian-flag-in-recognition-of-peace-and-community-contribution">fly the Palestinian flag for four day</a>s from today outside the Council Building on Burelli Street.</p>



<p class="">The symbolic gesture recognises the local Islamic community&#8217;s contributions and follows a Council resolution from August that reaffirmed Wollongong as a City for Peace.</p>



<p class="">The move comes after the Australian Government&#8217;s recognition of the State of Palestine at the United Nations in September.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Bayside Council</strong>&nbsp;has&nbsp;<a href="https://www.bayside.nsw.gov.au/your-council/latest-news/statement-le-sands-restaurant">issued a statement</a>&nbsp;defending its decision to end its lease with the family behind Le Sands restaurant after more than 40 years.</p>



<p class="">Council says the Antonopoulos family repeatedly breached their lease agreement and owes more than one hundred thousand dollars in outstanding payments.</p>



<p class="">The Brighton Pavilion building is now in need of substantial repairs worth an estimated one-point-five million dollars, with many defects attributed to lack of maintenance by the former tenant.</p>



<p class="">Work is underway to repair the building and reactivate the Pavilion for community benefit.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Shoalhaven City Council</strong>&nbsp;has raised concerns about the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.shoalhaven.nsw.gov.au/News-and-feedback/News-and-media/News/Council-concerned-about-proposed-site-for-new-school">proposed location for a new school</a>&nbsp;in the region.</p>



<p class="">The council believes the site may not be suitable for educational purposes. Issues include access, infrastructure, and environmental factors that could impact students and staff.</p>



<p class="">Mayor Patricia White is calling for further consultation with the state government, and the council is urging planners to consider alternative locations that better meet community needs.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Inner West</strong>&nbsp;Mayor Darcy Byrne has organised&nbsp;<a href="https://www.innerwest.nsw.gov.au/about/news/media-releases/2025-media-releases/rally-to-save-wests-tigers-convened">a rally to save the Wests Tigers</a>&nbsp;following the dismissal of all independent directors from the club&#8217;s board.</p>



<p class="">The rally will be held on Saturday, December 31st at Pratten Park, with fans marching to Wests Ashfield Leagues Club to demand the resignation of the Holman Barnes Group Board.</p>



<p class="">Mayor Byrne is calling on the NRL and Liquor and Gaming NSW to intervene in the club&#8217;s governance crisis.</p>



<p class="">He says the same people responsible for fifteen years of failure have now seized total control.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Balranald Shire Council</strong>&nbsp;has triumphed from hundreds of nominations to win at the 2025 Community Achievement Awards for New South Wales and the ACT for transforming the Balranald Discovery Centre precinct.</p>



<p class="">The project won the Council Crown Land Management Excellence Award for the upgrade of Heritage Park Reserve with interactive technology, new pavilions, and facilities that blend modern infrastructure with local heritage.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">NSW Briefs:</h2>



<p class=""><strong>Leeton Shire Council</strong>&nbsp;has won a Local Government NSW Environment Award&nbsp;<a href="https://www.leeton.nsw.gov.au/Your-Council/Council-News/Media-Releases/Leeton-Shire-Council-Wins-LGNSW-Environment-Award-for-Outstanding-FOGO-Rollout?utm_source=miragenews&amp;utm_medium=miragenews&amp;utm_campaign=news">for the exceptional success of its Food and Garden Organics waste service</a>.</p>



<p class="">The kerbside FOGO service, introduced in July last year, achieved a 60 percent diversion of organic waste from landfill in its first week with just 0.3 percent contamination.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Kiama Council</strong>&nbsp;has unveiled&nbsp;<a href="https://www.kiama.nsw.gov.au/Council/News/Kiama-Councils-new-online-policy-portal">a new online policy portal</a>&nbsp;to improve public access to council policies.</p>



<p class="">The digital platform aims to make it easier for residents to find and review important council documents.</p>



<p class="">Five local operators have joined the&nbsp;<strong>City of Newcastle</strong>&#8216;s Product Mentoring Development Program,&nbsp;<a href="https://newcastle.nsw.gov.au/about-us/news-and-updates/latest-news/local-businesses-looking-to-serve-up-more-reasons-to-visit-newcastle">aiming to develop bookable tourism experiences</a>&nbsp;to tap into the city&#8217;s $1.5 billion annual visitor market.</p>



<p class="">With Newcastle Airport expanding international routes, the program is helping businesses create experiences that give tourists more reasons to stay longer.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Fergal Coleman from Las Vegas</strong></p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Queensland Report</h2>



<p class=""><strong>Noosa Council</strong>&nbsp;is investigating&nbsp;<a href="https://www.noosa.qld.gov.au/About-Council/News-and-publications/Media-releases/2025/Deliberate-tree-poisoning-threatens-Noosa%E2%80%99s-environment">a deliberate act of environmental vandalism</a>&nbsp;at Sunshine Beach.</p>



<p class="">Six native trees have been poisoned, with bore holes drilled and chemicals applied.</p>



<p class="">The affected species are all critical for dune stabilisation and wildlife protection.</p>



<p class="">The Council’s Director Development and Regulation Richard MacGillivray said the council would be carrying out rehabilitation works and installing temporary signage to deter others from similar actions.</p>



<p class=""></p>



<p class="">Police Minister Dan Purdie has promised more State Flying Squad detectives will arrive in the&nbsp;<strong>South Burnett</strong>&nbsp;next week&nbsp;<a href="https://southburnett.com.au/news2/2025/12/02/councils-brief-mps-on-crime/">to tackle a recent crime spike</a>.</p>



<p class="">The Minister met with Attorney-General Deb Frecklington, senior police and council representatives on Tuesday to discuss juvenile crime and community safety concerns.</p>



<p class="">The ministers acknowledged more work needs to be done following serious concerns raised by South Burnett and Cherbourg councils.</p>



<p class="">Hervey Bay Airport has&nbsp;<a href="https://www.frasercoast.qld.gov.au/About-Council/Stay-Informed/News/Record-breaking-month-for-airport-as-Jetstar-launches-SALE">recorded its strongest month ever</a>&nbsp;with 21,654 passengers passing through in October.</p>



<p class="">Melbourne and Sydney routes are averaging 92 percent capacity, with passenger numbers up 7.26 percent from September.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Fraser Coast</strong>&nbsp;Mayor George Seymour says the record numbers are fantastic news for the Fraser Coast economy and tourism sector.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Cook Shire Council</strong>&nbsp;has&nbsp;<a href="https://www.cook.qld.gov.au/2025/11/27/funding-secured-for-more-solar-savings-in-cook-shire/">secured federal funding through the Solar for Public Facilities Program</a>&nbsp;for major solar upgrades at the Cooktown Events Centre and Bloomfield Hall.</p>



<p class="">The Events Centre will receive undercover solar parking similar to a recent installation at Council&#8217;s main building, helping cut its $100,000 annual electricity bill.</p>



<p class="">Mayor Robyn Holmes says the upgrades will help rein in escalating operational costs while maintaining community services.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Scenic Rim Regional Council</strong>&nbsp;has&nbsp;<a href="https://www.scenicrim.qld.gov.au/Our-Council/Connect-with-Council/News-and-Announcements/2025-News/Scenic-Rim-lands-trio-of-major-awards-in-standout-year-for-Council">secured three major state and national awards</a>&nbsp;to close out 2025, including a Silver Award at the Australasian Reporting Awards.</p>



<p class="">The Beaudesert Town Centre Revitalisation Project earned two honours at the IPWEA conference: Road Safety and Public Works Project of the Year.</p>



<p class="">The region also won Gold for Excellence in Food Tourism at the Queensland Tourism Awards for the Scenic Rim Eat Local Movement.</p>



<p class="">CEO David Keenan says the wins place the Scenic Rim among the better-performing regional councils in Queensland.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Tasmania</h2>



<p class="">Thirty council-managed roads in the&nbsp;<strong>Clarence City Counci</strong>l area&nbsp;<a href="https://www.ccc.tas.gov.au/2025/12/community-input-shapes-speed-limit-review-in-clarence/">are set for a speed limit review</a>&nbsp;after strong community feedback.</p>



<p class="">Residents nominated 75 roads during the Safer Speeds, Safer Roads engagement, with six additional roads now added to the shortlist.</p>



<p class="">The review aims to reduce crash risks for pedestrians, cyclists, and drivers on busy local routes.</p>



<p class="">Half of all community responses focused on speed limits, while others raised concerns about pedestrian crossings and road design.</p>



<p class="">Mahalia White-McColl has won the 2025&nbsp;<strong>Kingborough Council</strong>&nbsp;<a href="https://www.kingborough.tas.gov.au/2025/12/still-standing-wins-sculpture-award/">Acquisition Award for her sculpture &#8220;Still Standing&#8221;.</a></p>



<p class="">The piece combines recycled steel and ceramic mounted on an old sawmill cog. Its unique glaze is made from hardwood ash from local Tasmanian fires.</p>



<p class="">Acting Mayor Clare Glade-Wright praised the work for its artistic merit and environmental themes. The sculpture will be added to the Kingborough sculpture trail.</p>



<p class="">Five Tasmanian councils will share in $2.2M from the federal government, as part of a $50 million national program to upgrade community facilities with energy-efficient technology, including solar panels, batteries, and electric heating systems.</p>



<p class="">Meander Valley, Latrobe, Sorell, Burnie and George Town councils will be funded under second round of the government’s community energy upgrades fund.</p>



<p class="">The&nbsp;<strong>City of Launceston</strong>&nbsp;has won an Excellence Award from the Local Government Association of Tasmania for&nbsp;<a href="https://www.launceston.tas.gov.au/News-Media/City-of-Launceston-scores-Excellence-Award">using Minecraft as a community engagement tool.</a></p>



<p class="">Since 2021, Launceston has used LiDAR scans to create Minecraft maps of the city, allowing gamers to explore local landmarks like Cataract Gorge and City Park.</p>



<p class="">More than 800 Northern Tasmanian students tested the maps during National Science Week, and Mayor Matthew Garwood says it&#8217;s given young people a chance to reimagine their city&#8217;s open spaces and urban planning.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">South Australia</h2>



<p class="">Mayor&nbsp;<a href="https://www.franklinharbour.sa.gov.au/community/latest-news/resignation-of-mayor-robert-walsh">Robert Walsh has resigned</a>&nbsp;from the&nbsp;<strong>District Council of Franklin Harbour</strong>, effective December 2nd.</p>



<p class="">Cr Walsh served the community for eleven years with what council calls high distinction and integrity.</p>



<p class="">Deputy Mayor Rachel Deer is now acting in the mayoral role, while Council seeks advice from the Electoral Commission on conducting a supplementary election to fill the vacancy.</p>



<p class="">The&nbsp;<strong>City of Mount Gambier</strong>&nbsp;has&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mountgambier.sa.gov.au/news/council-opposes-environment-protection-reform-bill">formally opposed the Federal Government&#8217;s Environment Protection Reform Bill.</a></p>



<p class="">The Council fears the legislation gives too much power to the Environment Minister to approve projects in the national interest without proper consultation.</p>



<p class="">Mayor Lynette Martin says the changes risk reducing transparency and limiting community input on critical decisions.</p>



<p class="">Council is particularly concerned about impacts on the Limestone Coast&#8217;s agricultural land and groundwater resources.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Peterborough District Council</strong>&nbsp;has appointed Deirdre Albrighton&nbsp;<a href="https://www.peterborough.sa.gov.au/district-info/latest-news/leadership-update">as Acting CEO until November 2026.</a></p>



<p class="">Kristen Clark, who&#8217;s been Acting CEO since May, will transition to a consultant role focusing on finance and infrastructure.</p>



<p class="">Ms Albrighton will oversee governance, community engagement, and the 2026 council elections, while Mr Clark will continue critical strategic work including the Long Term Financial Plan and Asset Management Plan.</p>



<p class="">The arrangement ensures a smooth transition through the upcoming local government election process.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Western Australia</h2>



<p class="">Perth&#8217;s Lord Mayor Bruce Reynolds has abandoned his controversial $125,000 workplace culture review after intense public backlash and legal challenges, throwing the City of Perth into crisis&nbsp;<a href="https://www.abc.net.au/news/2025-12-03/perth-lord-mayor-backs-down-from-workplace-culture-review/106097614">according to ABC News.</a></p>



<p class="">The review, which Reynolds pushed through with just six minutes&#8217; notice to councillors, has sparked accusations of poor governance and misuse of public funds.</p>



<p class="">The decision prompted the resignation of acting CEO Peta Mabbs, who published a scathing report declaring the rushed decision unlawful.</p>



<p class="">Mabbs&#8217; departure has added to the turmoil at the council, which is already facing significant scrutiny over its handling of the matter.</p>



<p class="">Angry ratepayers packed Tuesday&#8217;s council meeting, with some questioning why the funds weren&#8217;t being allocated to pressing issues like homelessness and public safety instead. Others directly accused the mayor of poor governance in approving such a significant expenditure with minimal deliberation.</p>



<p class=""><a href="http://www.watoday.com.au/politics/western-australia/city-of-perth-turmoil-intensifies-as-lord-mayor-hands-workplace-probe-to-local-government-inspector-20251202-p5nkbe.html">WA Today reported that</a>&nbsp;Reynolds now plans to refer the workplace culture concerns to the incoming Local Government Inspector rather than proceeding with the external review. He maintains he acted in good faith over staff welfare concerns raised by former employees.</p>



<p class="">A revocation motion to formally cancel the workplace review will be voted on at next week&#8217;s council meeting, where councillors will have the opportunity to reverse the controversial decision that has engulfed Perth&#8217;s local government in controversy.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Global Report</h2>



<p class="">UK:</p>



<p class="">Reform UK has reportedly launched an urgent investigation into&nbsp;<strong>Staffordshire County Council</strong>&nbsp;leader Ian Cooper over alleged racist social media posts.</p>



<p class="">The activist group Hope Not Hate claims to have found posts on an X account linked to Cooper, including one stating foreign nationals shouldn&#8217;t sit in Parliament.</p>



<p class="">Nine Labour MPs and Conservative councillors have called for his immediate resignation,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/crk726m7j73o">according to BBC News.</a></p>



<p class=""><a href="https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/c5yjg2r7z9zo">In breaking news</a>, the UK government has delayed mayoral elections in four English regions—<strong>Greater Essex, Norfolk &amp; Suffolk, Hampshire &amp; the Solent, and Sussex &amp; Brighton</strong>—from May 2026 to May 2028, citing the need for more time to complete local government reorganisation into unitary authorities.</p>



<p class="">The delays have been criticised as &#8220;subverting democracy,&#8221; with concerns that further elections may be cancelled, while the government maintains that the postponement allows for proper establishment of combined authorities before mayors take office.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Dublin City Council</strong>&nbsp;has reportedly withdrawn a controversial proposal to rename Herzog Park, which honours former Israeli President Chaim Herzog.</p>



<p class="">The move faced strong criticism from Irish officials and Israel, with concerns it could be seen as antisemitic,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.ynetnews.com/article/rkqrmmcwwe">according to Y Net News</a>.</p>



<p class=""><a href="https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/ckgdxngdjrvo">BBC News has reported on</a>&nbsp;how&nbsp;<strong>West Dunbartonshire Council</strong>&nbsp;attempted to hire external contractors to remove flags from lampposts after council workers faced verbal abuse from members of the public, but no bids were received for the work.</p>



<p class="">The flags, which were put up following a social media campaign linked to anti-asylum seeker protests, are banned under Scottish road laws. Similar incidents of worker intimidation have occurred in other Scottish councils including&nbsp;<strong>Aberdeen</strong>&nbsp;and&nbsp;<strong>Aberdeenshire</strong>.</p>



<p class="">Highway workers in&nbsp;<strong>Cambridgeshire</strong>&nbsp;have faced a shocking wave of abuse while on the job.</p>



<p class=""><a href="https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/c2lv0e2lz77o">BBC News reported that</a>&nbsp;since November 2024, there have been 29 instances of threatening behaviour and four assaults on staff. Incidents include spitting, bottle throwing, hair pulling, and a woman ramming her vehicle into barriers.</p>



<p class="">Workers are now wearing bodycams to combat the violence.</p>



<p class="">USA:</p>



<p class="">Thirty-five county clerks from across&nbsp;<strong>Colorado</strong>&nbsp;are urging Governor Jared Polis&nbsp;<a href="https://www.denvergov.org/Government/Agencies-Departments-Offices/Agencies-Departments-Offices-Directory/Denver-Clerk-and-Recorder/About-the-Denver-Clerk-and-Recorder/communications-and-engagement/media-releases/2025/Colorado-County-Clerks-Urge-Governor-Polis-to-Keep-Convicted-Former-Clerk-Tina-Peters-in-State-Custody">to keep convicted former Mesa County Clerk Tina Peters in state custody</a>.</p>



<p class="">The clerks say Peters&#8217; illegal actions have led to heightened threats against election workers and erosion of voter confidence, and releasing her would send the wrong signal and pander to ongoing attacks on election integrity.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Boston</strong>&nbsp;has joined eleven other jurisdictions in&nbsp;<a href="https://www.boston.gov/news/boston-joins-local-governments-and-nonprofits-challenge-new-federal-restrictions-housing">suing the Trump administration</a>&nbsp;over changes to a critical homelessness program.</p>



<p class="">The changes threaten forty-eight million dollars in annual funding that supports over two thousand formerly homeless households in Boston.</p>



<p class="">Mayor Michelle Wu warns the new restrictions could push more than eleven hundred Bostonians back onto the streets.</p>



<p class=""><strong>New Jersey</strong>&nbsp;Governor-elect Mikie Sherrill has announced a bipartisan Local Government Advisory Group to guide her transition into office.</p>



<p class=""><a href="https://www.insidernj.com/governor-elect-sherrill-announces-transition-local-government-advisory-group/">According to Insider New Jersey,</a>&nbsp;the group comprises elected officials from across New Jersey who will provide expertise to ensure local communities have a voice in the new administration.</p>



<p class="">CANADA:</p>



<p class=""><strong>London City Council</strong>&nbsp;has&nbsp;<a href="https://www.ctvnews.ca/london/article/council-considers-banning-e-scooters-from-london-streets-permission-briefly-extended/">narrowly voted to extend the city&#8217;s e-scooter pilot project</a>&nbsp;by six months after nearly banning the devices immediately.</p>



<p class="">There was a push for an outright ban, due to overwhelming complaints about dangerous and inconsiderate behaviour by riders.</p>



<p class="">The pilot will expire next May.</p>



<p class="">A garbage truck driver in Toronto has been&nbsp;<a href="https://www.ctvnews.ca/toronto/article/garbage-truck-driver-struck-and-killed-in-scarborough-toronto-police/">fatally struck while working on his route</a>.</p>



<p class="">The 66 year old man as an employee of&nbsp;<strong>Toronto City Counci</strong>l, and it appears he was struck by his own vehicle. Police are investigating the incident.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Calgary Council</strong>&nbsp;has cut climate funding and boosted transit spending as its budget talks continue.&nbsp;<a href="https://www.ctvnews.ca/calgary/article/council-cuts-climate-funding-boosts-transit-spending-as-budget-talks-continue/">CTV News reported the</a>&nbsp;decision has sparked debate about the city&#8217;s priorities in addressing environmental concerns versus transportation infrastructure needs.</p>



<p class="">NZ:</p>



<p class=""><a href="https://wanakaapp.nz/NewsStory/local-mayors-respond-to-reform-proposals/692fb9677563a5002ef121c4">The Wanaka App has reported</a>&nbsp;more reaction to new central government reforms of local government in New Zealand.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Ruapehu</strong>&nbsp;mayor Weston Kirton has warned that the government&#8217;s new rates cap will disproportionately impact infrastructure-stressed rural councils like his.</p>



<p class=""><a href="https://www.rnz.co.nz/news/ldr/580818/rates-cap-will-hit-tourism-districts-ruapehu-mayor">Radio New Zealand reported the</a>&nbsp;district faces significant challenges with ageing bridges, heavy tourism loads, and major capital needs, but lacks alternative funding sources.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Queenstown Lakes District Council</strong>&nbsp;mayor John Glover has expressed concern that the reforms that are being portrayed as reducing bureaucracy but in reality also aim to merge smaller district councils.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Central Otago</strong>&nbsp;mayor Tamah Alley noted the proposals signal a pathway toward unitary councils and stressed the importance of local people making local decisions.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Wellington City Council</strong>&nbsp;has installed motion-activated cameras on Matairangi Mount Victoria after&nbsp;<a href="https://wellington.govt.nz/news-and-events/news-and-information/our-wellington/2025/12/mt-vic-track-vandalism">deliberate vandalism targeting mountain bikers.</a></p>



<p class="">Logs, stumps and timber have been fastened to trees at rider height on several trails, creating serious injury risks. Fencing and signage have also been removed in various locations.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://lgnewsroundup.com/subverting-democracy-councillors-suspended-and-accosted-525/">&#8220;Subverting democracy&#8221;, councillors suspended and accosted &#8211; #525</a> appeared first on <a href="https://lgnewsroundup.com">Local Government News Roundup</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<post-id xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">6722</post-id>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Rate cap breach, intervention and a tragic loss &#8211; ft.Anne-Marie Cade #524</title>
		<link>https://lgnewsroundup.com/rate-cap-breach-intervention-and-a-tragic-loss-ft-anne-marie-cade-524/?utm_source=rss&#038;utm_medium=rss&#038;utm_campaign=rate-cap-breach-intervention-and-a-tragic-loss-ft-anne-marie-cade-524</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[LG News Roundup]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 20:43:25 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[New episode]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[International]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[NSW]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[QLD]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[South Australia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tasmania]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Victoria]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Western Australia]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://lgnewsroundup.com/?p=6720</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>In this edition of the Local Government News Roundup: Also today: Conflict resolution expert and former mayor Anne-Marie Cade has been watching councils elect their mayors, and has advice for navigating what can be a challenging period for some. The Local Government News Roundup is brought to you by the&#160;Victorian Local Governance Association, the national [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://lgnewsroundup.com/rate-cap-breach-intervention-and-a-tragic-loss-ft-anne-marie-cade-524/">Rate cap breach, intervention and a tragic loss &#8211; ft.Anne-Marie Cade #524</a> appeared first on <a href="https://lgnewsroundup.com">Local Government News Roundup</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p class="">In this edition of the Local Government News Roundup:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li class="">A second Victorian council in breach of the rate cap</li>



<li class="">Hume Council wins VCAT action against illegal earthworks</li>



<li class="">New figures show the chronic underfunding that is holding back housing development</li>



<li class="">A proposal to fund Pride Month activities under fire</li>



<li class="">A council backs away from a special rate variation plan</li>



<li class="">The Queensland government to send an adviser into Redland Council</li>



<li class="">The tragic death of a WA deputy shire president in a bushfire</li>
</ul>



<p class="">Also today:</p>



<p class="">Conflict resolution expert and former mayor Anne-Marie Cade has been watching councils elect their mayors, and has advice for navigating what can be a challenging period for some.</p>



<p class="">The Local Government News Roundup is brought to you by the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.vlga.org.au/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Victorian Local Governance Association</a>, the national broadcaster on all things local government; with support from <a href="http://www.symphony3.com">Symphony3</a> &#8211; simple, connected customer experiences.</p>



<p class=""><a href="https://www.buzzsprout.com/1726495/episodes/18288221-rate-cap-breach-intervention-and-a-tragic-loss-ft-anne-marie-cade-524" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Listen to the episode here.</a></p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<p class="">Read along with all the news from this episode below:</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Victorian Report</h2>



<p class="">It’s been revealed that a second Victorian council has breached the state’s rate cap this year.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Alpine Shire Council</strong>&nbsp;<a href="https://www.alpineshire.vic.gov.au/news/council-taking-steps-rectify-202526-rate-cap-breach">has confirmed the breach</a>, blaming it on a system error that led to rates being calculated incorrectly.</p>



<p class="">The error resulted in an average rate increase of 3.96% instead of the mandated 3% cap, collecting an extra $168,304 from ratepayers.</p>



<p class="">The mistake occurred when a rating system provider applied a classification change earlier than advised, throwing off the base rate calculations.</p>



<p class="">Council CEO Will Jeremy said there was no intention to exceed the cap, and there&#8217;s no penalty or fine for the breach.</p>



<p class="">The Council will consider how to rectify the breach at its December meeting.</p>



<p class="">It is likely that it will adjust next year&#8217;s rates to be at least $168,304 lower than they would otherwise be.</p>



<p class="">The breach is one of two reported by the Essential Services Commission in its&nbsp;<a href="https://newshub.medianet.com.au/2025/12/alpine-and-hindmarsh-councils-not-compliant-with-rate-caps/131428/">annual compliance report on the rate cap</a>&#8211; in September this year,&nbsp;<strong>Hindmarsh Shire Council</strong>&nbsp;<a href="https://www.hindmarsh.vic.gov.au/Council/News-and-Media/Latest-News/20252026-Rate-Cap-Calculation">admitted to an error</a>&nbsp;that saw it raise nearly $4,000 above the cap.</p>



<p class="">The ESC said it was the first time since 2020/21 that the cap had been exceeded.</p>



<p class="">It also noted that Ballarat and Bayside Councils did not increase rates at all this year, and that higher rate caps had been approved for Hepburn and Indigo Shires.</p>



<p class="">Eight councils introduced new service charges to recover costs for waste management services.</p>



<p class="">The Victorian Civil and Administrative Tribunal has issued&nbsp;<a href="https://www.hume.vic.gov.au/Residents/Latest-News/News-and-Media-Releases/2025/VCAT-orders-halt-illegal-earthworks-on-Sunbury-properties">enforcement orders stopping illegal earthworks</a>&nbsp;on three Sunbury properties.</p>



<p class="">The orders follow&nbsp;<strong>Hume City Council</strong>&nbsp;action over works that breached planning rules designed to protect the environment.</p>



<p class="">No further earthworks can proceed without council approval or a planning permit.</p>



<p class="">Council will monitor the sites to ensure compliance and thanked residents for their vigilance.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Northern Grampians Shire Council</strong>&nbsp;will&nbsp;<a href="https://www.ngshire.vic.gov.au/Latest-News/News-Directory/Council-to-review-community-care-services">review its community care services</a>&nbsp;in light of major federal aged care reforms.</p>



<p class="">The new Aged Care Act shifts funding from block grants to fee-for-service models, allowing clients to choose their own providers, and CEO Brent McAlister says the council must determine whether to remain a service provider or shift to advocacy and navigation roles.</p>



<p class="">Community engagement will begin in January with surveys and workshops in Stawell and St Arnaud.</p>



<p class="">No decisions have been made yet, and the council emphasises this is a genuine consultation process.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Murrindindi Shire Council</strong>&nbsp;has released&nbsp;<a href="https://www.murrindindi.vic.gov.au/Council/News-and-Media/Council-News/Council-releases-community-healthcare-survey-results">survey results on a proposed health service merger.</a></p>



<p class="">The 16-day survey attracted 278 responses about the voluntary amalgamation between Alexandra District Health and Eastern Health.</p>



<p class="">Most respondents expressed concern about potential impacts on local services and decision-making.</p>



<p class="">A smaller group supported the proposal, citing possible benefits like improved specialist access.</p>



<p class="">Mayor Damien Gallagher said the results reinforce the importance of ensuring the community is fully informed and actively involved.</p>



<p class="">He said the Council will share the results with both health boards to inform their decision-making.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Horsham Rural City Council</strong>&nbsp;has voted&nbsp;<a href="https://www.hrcc.vic.gov.au/Our-Council/News-and-Media/Latest-News/reopening-the-wesley">to commit funding to reopen The Wesley</a>, the town&#8217;s beloved performing arts venue closed since 2017.</p>



<p class="">A community fundraising campaign raised over $423,000, with Council contributing $2.28 million toward the $2.70 million project cost.</p>



<p class="">The venue is expected to boost the local economy by $300,000 annually through visitor spending.</p>



<p class="">Built in 1912, The Wesley was Victoria&#8217;s only independent Performing Arts Centre when it opened in 1998.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Yarra Ranges Council</strong>&nbsp;has endorsed&nbsp;<a href="https://www.yarraranges.vic.gov.au/Our-Council/Latest-news/Council-sets-advocacy-priorities-for-2025-27">a new advocacy platform</a>&nbsp;to guide its conversations with State and Federal Governments ahead of the 2026 State Election.</p>



<p class="">The priorities include safe road crossings on state-managed roads, more affordable housing, additional funding for the Yarra Valley Trail, and better public transport.</p>



<p class="">Mayor Richard Higgins says the platform reflects community feedback and expert analysis.</p>



<p class="">Key asks include funding for a new aquatics facility to replace the closed Kilsyth Pool and pedestrian crossings along the Warburton Highway.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Hepburn Shire Council</strong>&nbsp;has&nbsp;<a href="https://www.hepburn.vic.gov.au/Council/News/Latest-news/Surplus-Council-land-sale-approved-with-safeguards-for-Rea-Lands-Park">approved the sale of seven surplus properties</a>, five of which have been earmarked for affordable housing development.</p>



<p class="">The decision follows community consultation that began in July 2025.</p>



<p class="">Proceeds from the sales will fund a financial reserve to support future grant applications.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Yarriambiack Shire Council</strong>&nbsp;has identified two former depot sites at Hopetoun as surplus to requirements, and has commenced community consultation on a proposal to sell the land.</p>



<p class="">The sites were identified as part of a&nbsp;<a href="https://www.yarriambiack.vic.gov.au/Home/Tabs/News/Proposal-to-Sell-Land-%E2%80%93-Former-Depot-Sites-in-Hopetoun">review of the shire’s financial health</a>, and a need to reduce expenditure.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Frankston City Council</strong>&nbsp;is addressing&nbsp;<a href="https://www.frankston.vic.gov.au/Council/News-and-media/Latest-News/Media-Release-2025/Statement-from-Mayor-Bolam-Protecting-Frankston-City%E2%80%99s-Coastline">public concern over alleged illegal works</a>&nbsp;and vegetation removal across the municipality, including along the foreshore.</p>



<p class="">Mayor Kris Bolam said the Council is working closely with the Victorian Department of Energy, Environment and Climate Action on enforcement for coastal Crown land.</p>



<p class="">Earlier this year, a landowner was found guilty on multiple charges relating to unlawful mass vegetation removal at a Langwarrin property.</p>



<p class="">Council says development and sustainability must go hand in hand, with protecting foreshore, reserves and green spaces remaining a core priority.</p>



<p class="">Residents witnessing illegal vegetation removal are encouraged to contact Council&#8217;s Planning Investigations Team.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Corangamite Shire Council</strong>&nbsp;has adopted&nbsp;<a href="https://www.corangamite.vic.gov.au/Council/News-and-Media/Latest-News/Camperdown-and-Terang-Structure-Plans-adopted">structure plans for Camperdown and Terang</a>, mapping out development for the towns over the next 15 to 20 years.</p>



<p class="">Mayor Kate Makin said the plans aim to support growth while protecting each town&#8217;s unique character, following a year of community consultation.</p>



<p class="">Key priorities include more diverse housing options, better pedestrian access, and support for local businesses and tourism.</p>



<p class="">Both plans feature a two-storey height limit and rezoning of certain areas for residential and commercial use. They will now inform future planning scheme amendments to implement the recommendations.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Victorian Briefs</h2>



<p class=""><strong>Monash Council</strong>&nbsp;has received $1 million from the Victorian Government&nbsp;<a href="https://www.monash.vic.gov.au/About-Us/News/Funding-towards-Glen-Waverleys-future-new-library">to build a new library in Glen Waverley</a>&nbsp;as part of a $100 million+ civic precinct.</p>



<p class="">Mayor Stuart James said the new library will serve as a hub for a community expected to boom over the next 10 years as new housing is delivered around the Suburban Rail Loop.</p>



<p class="">The&nbsp;<strong>City of Casey</strong>&nbsp;has won the 2025 National Growth Areas Alliance Strategic Foresight &amp; Innovation Award&nbsp;<a href="https://www.casey.vic.gov.au/news/city-of-casey-wins-national-award-innovative-green-streets-project">for its Green Streets in Orana project</a>, which plants 2 to 2.5 trees per lot to achieve over 30% canopy cover—more than double the industry standard.</p>



<p class="">The award was shared with the City of Armadale, WA for its advocacy priorities strategy.</p>



<p class="">The&nbsp;<strong>City of Greater Bendigo</strong>&nbsp;has unveiled&nbsp;<a href="https://www.bendigo.vic.gov.au/about-us/news-and-media/city-launches-new-emergency-dashboard-help-residents-stay-safe">a new Emergency Dashboard on its website</a>&nbsp;to help residents access critical information during bushfires, floods, and other emergencies.</p>



<p class="">The dashboard features real-time warnings, weather updates, road closures, and relief centre locations, all in one mobile-friendly platform.</p>



<p class="">More than 82,000 new homes that could begin construction today remain unbuilt due to a lack of sewers, roads and other enabling infrastructure,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.ngaa.org.au/resources/media-release-over-82-000-homes-unbuilt-due-to-outdated-government-vision">according to the National Growth Areas Alliance.</a></p>



<p class="">Growth Areas account for just 5% of councils but are set to deliver 26% of new housing development, yet chronic underfunding is creating critical supply bottlenecks.</p>



<p class="">A third of all potential home builds are held up due to infrastructure lags, with some entire estates already living without connected sewerage.</p>



<p class="">The National Growth Areas Alliance is calling on government to urgently align commonwealth funding to where people want to live to meet National Housing Accord targets.</p>



<p class="">It says that without action, the planned 300,000 new homes in these communities won&#8217;t be built by the 2029 deadline.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">NSW Report</h2>



<p class="">An experienced local government administrator has been appointed to oversee the separation of&nbsp;<strong>Cootamundra-Gundagai Regional Council.</strong></p>



<p class="">Peter Bascomb will guide the complex process of splitting the merged council back into two separate entities, and has already begun coordinating early planning and meeting with staff.</p>



<p class="">The Council said&nbsp;<a href="https://www.cgrc.nsw.gov.au/2025/12/02/appointment-of-peter-bascomb-to-lead-councils-demerger-transition/">his expertise in managing complex structural change</a>&nbsp;will be critical as the council navigates this sensitive process.</p>



<p class="">That news comes as work continues to finalise the referendum result at Snowy Valleys Regional Council.</p>



<p class="">A decisive 87 per cent YES vote on the weekend makes the outcome clear, but the final result will not be declared until December 15, and then it will be up to the local government minister to determine next steps.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Lane Cove Council</strong>&nbsp;is facing backlash over a proposal to grant up to $5,000 to local pubs and clubs to host drag shows during Pride Month 2026,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.dailytelegraph.com.au/newslocal/north-shore/lane-cove-ratepayers-push-back-against-council-bid-to-grant-funds-for-local-drag-shows/news-story/f4f2507cd468b5e0bdba009fa84891c7">according to the Daily Telegraph</a>.</p>



<p class="">Labor councillor Katie Little says the grants would support the LGBTQIA+ community and boost business for local venues during a quiet time of year.</p>



<p class="">Conservative ratepayers argue the funding is inappropriate for the family-oriented area and should be directed to essential services instead.</p>



<p class="">The council will vote on the motion at its December 11 meeting.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Blacktown City Council</strong>&nbsp;has voted&nbsp;<a href="https://www.blacktown.nsw.gov.au/News-Media/Blacktown-City-Council-decision-on-proposed-Special-Rate-Variation">against applying for a Special Rate Variation</a>.</p>



<p class="">The decision came after 42 days of community consultation that received more than 3,800 submissions.</p>



<p class="">Mayor Brad Bunting says the council respects the outcome but warns underlying financial challenges remain.</p>



<p class="">He said it was a close vote, and has pledged to continue looking at options to support the rapidly growing city.</p>



<p class="">The historic dive tower at Lambton Park War Memorial Swimming Centre&nbsp;<a href="https://newcastle.nsw.gov.au/about-us/news-and-updates/latest-news/media-statement-%E2%80%93-lambton-park-war-memorial-swimming-centre-dive-tower">has been temporarily closed</a>&nbsp;following safety concerns raised by SafeWork NSW with the&nbsp;<strong>City of Newcastle</strong>.</p>



<p class="">Built in 1963, the tower is one of only two heritage diving facilities still operating in Australia. SafeWork inspections identified fall and slip risks on the tower and springboards.</p>



<p class="">The city is now conducting a risk assessment and consulting with the local dive club&#8217;s 70 members about the facility&#8217;s future.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Wingecarribee Shire Council</strong>&nbsp;has won a major court battle&nbsp;<a href="https://www.wsc.nsw.gov.au/News/Media-Release/Council-Wins-Court-Action-Over-Serious-Planning-Breaches">over illegal development works in Bowral.</a></p>



<p class="">The Land and Environment Court convicted property owner Serge Golman and Lake House Bowral Pty Ltd of serious planning breaches for unauthorised works that included extensions to a dwelling, conversion of farming stables into living quarters, and the destruction of over 5,000 square metres of protected forest.</p>



<p class="">The Court ordered combined penalties of $360,000 plus payment of the council’s costs.</p>



<p class="">Council says the judgment sends a clear message that unlawful development will be met with firm action.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Bayside Council</strong>&nbsp;is&nbsp;<a href="https://www.bayside.nsw.gov.au/your-council/latest-news/council-advocates-bexley-station">pushing for a train station at Bexley</a>&nbsp;on the proposed Kogarah to Parramatta rail line.</p>



<p class="">The council says Bexley experiences significant traffic pressures from toll avoidance and limited public transport options. A station would improve access for residents and businesses while supporting revitalisation of the Bexley Town Centre.</p>



<p class="">Council will write to the Transport Minister and local MPs outlining the case for the station.</p>



<p class="">The Sydney Portugal Community Club in Marrickville has been approved by&nbsp;<strong>Inner West Council</strong>&nbsp;<a href="https://www.innerwest.nsw.gov.au/about/news/media-releases/2025-media-releases/large-scale-events-sydney-portugal-community-club">to host large-scale outdoor events.</a></p>



<p class="">The club can now hold five events with up to 5,000 patrons and ten smaller events with up to 3,500 patrons annually.</p>



<p class="">Mayor Darcy Byrne says it will strengthen the Inner West&#8217;s position as Sydney&#8217;s live music and entertainment hub.</p>



<p class="">The club aims to celebrate Portuguese culture while contributing to Marrickville&#8217;s diverse community.</p>



<p class="">Farmers on the Western Plains have new drought resilience tools&nbsp;<a href="https://www.warren.nsw.gov.au/council/media-releases/detail/country-heartline-launches-at-callubri-station">thanks to the Country Heartline Project.</a></p>



<p class="">Launched at Callubri Station, the tri-council initiative helps landholders build agritourism ventures and strengthen farm viability.</p>



<p class="">New resources include an Agritourism Startup Handbook and three curated visitor trails showcasing farm life, cultural heritage, and natural wonders.</p>



<p class="">The project is funded through the NSW Regional Drought Resilience Planning Program, and is designed to create alternative income streams when seasonal conditions are challenging.</p>



<p class="">The three councils involved are&nbsp;<strong>Warren, Bogan and Coonamble Shires</strong>.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">NSW Briefs:</h2>



<p class=""><strong>Liverpool Plains Shire Council</strong>&nbsp;has&nbsp;<a href="https://www.liverpoolplains.nsw.gov.au/Media/Quirindi-Aquatic-Centre-Officially-Opened">officially opened the brand new Quirindi Aquatic Centre</a>&nbsp;just in time for summer.</p>



<p class="">Construction of the $6.6M facility was funded through the NSW Government’s Resources for Regions Program.</p>



<p class="">Greg Hill has commenced his new role as General Manager of&nbsp;<strong>Coonamble Shire Council</strong>, moving from his previous role at&nbsp;<strong>Central Darling Shire</strong>.</p>



<p class="">Mayor Daniel Keady&nbsp;<a href="https://www.facebook.com/share/p/1AHUtT7N1b/">welcomed Mr Hill to the council</a>&nbsp;on Monday, and thanked outgoing Interim General Manager Phillip Perram for his contribution to the shire in recent months.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Eurobodalla Shire Council</strong>&nbsp;has approved a proposal for Moruya to become officially recognised as an RV-friendly destination.</p>



<p class="">Overnight parking in the town centre has been ruled out of the two-year trial, with stays limited to approved caravan parks and camping grounds.</p>



<p class="">Support for the Roundup comes from Symphony3.</p>



<p class="">Symphony3’s SmartGlue solution helps councils deliver&nbsp;<strong>simple connected customer experiences</strong>.</p>



<p class="">Like Ballina Shire Council who recently streamlined and automated their register of payments delivering a beautiful online experience to citizens and getting a positive Return on Investment within 5 weeks.</p>



<p class="">SmartGlue eliminates 30- 40 minutes of manual labour per payment at Ballina. With over 8,000 payment transactions per annum this new service eliminates over 5,000 hours of manual labour per annum.</p>



<p class="">Visit&nbsp;<a href="http://www.symphony3.com/">www.symphony3.com</a>&nbsp;to learn how SmartGlue can work for you.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Queensland Report</h2>



<p class="">A governance adviser has been appointed to&nbsp;<strong>Redland City Council</strong>&nbsp;after it led Queensland with 114 councillor complaints in the last financial year.</p>



<p class="">Mayor Jos Mitchell has received at least 47 complaints since taking office in 2024, though she claims the anonymous system has been weaponised against her,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.brisbanetimes.com.au/national/queensland/governance-adviser-appointed-for-complaint-plagued-bayside-council-20251201-p5njxe.html">according to the Brisbane Times.</a></p>



<p class="">The adviser will work with the council until May, focusing on leadership, communication, and councillor conduct.</p>



<p class="">Mayor Mitchell is also locked in a defamation lawsuit with the council&#8217;s top legal officer.</p>



<p class="">The intervention follows calls from the mayor herself for external support. The identity of the adviser is yet to be announced.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Noosa Council</strong>&nbsp;is looking to thousands of empty bedrooms across the shire&nbsp;<a href="https://www.noosa.qld.gov.au/About-Council/News-and-publications/Media-releases/2025/Spare-rooms-key-to-solving-Noosa%E2%80%99s-housing-crisis">as a solution to the local housing crisis.</a></p>



<p class="">Most homes have three to four bedrooms but are occupied by just one or two people, and the Council is exploring ways to encourage homeowners to take in lodgers or local workers.</p>



<p class="">The initiative could help people share housing costs while providing much-needed accommodation for those struggling to find homes.</p>



<p class="">An innovative platypus monitoring project has revealed the platypus population in&nbsp;<strong>City of Moreton Bay</strong>&nbsp;is more widespread than initially thought.</p>



<p class="">The project&nbsp;<a href="https://www.moretonbay.qld.gov.au/News/Media/Platypus-population-paddling-strongly-in-City-of-Moreton-Bay">has confirmed the presence of platypus</a>&nbsp;– a species known for its elusive behaviour – in at least 37 creeks and rivers across the City.</p>



<p class="">It even positively detected platypus DNA in Conflagration Creek at a major industrial area.</p>



<p class="">The project – now in its third year &#8211; will help Council to safeguard platypus habitat though proactive management of the species and their environment to aid long-term survival.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Mapoon Aboriginal Shire Council</strong>&nbsp;will hold a special meeting on Wednesday, 1st December, at which will consider an item regarding&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mapoon.qld.gov.au/News/Notice-of-Special-Council-Meeting">the appointment of a chief executive officer</a>.</p>



<p class="">While at&nbsp;<strong>Yarrabah Aboriginal Shire Council,</strong>&nbsp;Michael Miller&nbsp;<a href="https://www.yarrabah.qld.gov.au/public-notice-appointment-of-ceo/">has taken up the CEO position</a>&nbsp;in recent weeks, making the move from the Waanyi Native Title Aboriginal Corporation.</p>



<p class="">And&nbsp;<strong>Brisbane City Council</strong>&#8216;s General Manager of Strategy and Network Services Jessica Paton is heading south to take up the Chief Executive Officer role at Metro Tasmania. She officially starts there on January 19.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Tasmania</h2>



<p class="">The&nbsp;<strong>City of Launceston</strong>&nbsp;has unveiled a major organisational restructure that will impact up to 25 staff members,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.themercury.com.au/news/tasmania/up-to-25-jobs-on-the-line-at-launceston-council-due-to-project-shape/news-story/53a9c744ce428bb45e15aea772d0beb9">according to The Mercury.</a></p>



<p class="">Chief executive Sam Johnson insists that Project Shape is not about cutting costs, but aligning the council&#8217;s structure with its strategic plan.</p>



<p class="">The affected workers, representing four percent of the 600-strong workforce, will be offered redeployment or voluntary redundancy.</p>



<p class="">The move comes as the council pursues ambitious goals including building 4,300 new homes by 2035 and growing the population by 30,000.</p>



<p class="">Employee benefits totalled around 55 million dollars in the latest financial year, the council&#8217;s largest expense.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Kingborough Council</strong>&nbsp;has unanimously&nbsp;<a href="https://tasmaniafc.com/news/high-performance-centre-da-unanimously-approved/">approved the Tasmania Devils&#8217; new high-performance centre</a>&nbsp;in Kingston.</p>



<p class="">The new AFL and AFLW facility will include a full gymnasium, indoor training field, specialist rooms, and an 80-seat lecture theatre.</p>



<p class="">It will accommodate about 80 staff and feature public spaces including a cafe and merchandise store.</p>



<p class="">Construction tendering is set to begin early next year.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">South Australia</h2>



<p class=""><strong>West Torrens Council</strong>&nbsp;has been forced to scale back its ambitious 30-million-dollar redevelopment of Richmond Oval after failing to secure 23 million dollars in government funding.</p>



<p class="">The original plans included a new grandstand, netball courts, and expanded parking for the West Adelaide Football Club home ground.</p>



<p class=""><a href="https://www.adelaidenow.com.au/news/south-australia/ambitious-richmond-oval-development-scaled-back-after-council-unable-to-secure-23-million-in-government-funding/news-story/d8bf1a4295c8073f617344650309d2a2">Adelaide Now reported that</a>&nbsp;the Council will now focus on upgrading the aging Grandstand and building new changerooms with its approved 7 million dollar budget.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Alexandrina Council</strong>&nbsp;has recognised 152 volunteers who&nbsp;<a href="https://www.alexandrina.sa.gov.au/__data/assets/pdf_file/0034/1906558/Media-release-Volunteer-Recognition-Day-2025.pdf">contributed more than 7,300 hours of service</a>&nbsp;over the past year.</p>



<p class="">The volunteers were honored at a special recognition event held at Centenary Hall in Goolwa, themed &#8220;Sustainability in Action.&#8221;</p>



<p class="">More than 20 volunteers received certificates for 10 years or more of service, with four volunteers recognised for 15 years.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Western Australia</h2>



<p class="">The small farming community of&nbsp;<strong>Ravensthorpe</strong>&nbsp;in Western Australia&#8217;s Great Southern region is mourning the loss of its deputy shire president, who died while defending his property from a devastating bushfire this week.</p>



<p class=""><a href="https://www.abc.net.au/news/2025-12-02/mark-mudie-identified-as-farmer-killed-in-ravensthorpe-fire/106093572">ABC News reported that</a>&nbsp;fifty-nine-year-old Mark Mudie was killed on Monday afternoon while operating a front-end loader to establish a firebreak on his family&#8217;s farm at West River, near Ravensthorpe.</p>



<p class="">His vehicle became engulfed by flames as a fast-moving bushfire, described by authorities as &#8220;treacherous,&#8221; swept through five-thousand hectares during peak harvest season.</p>



<p class="">Mark Mudie had farmed in the region with his wife Elaine for 35 years and was an experienced member of the local bushfire brigade.</p>



<p class="">In a statement, the Shire of Ravensthorpe&nbsp;<a href="https://www.ravensthorpe.wa.gov.au/news/statement-from-the-shire-of-ravensthorpe/712">said it was &#8220;devastated&#8221; by the loss</a>, with thoughts going out to Mr Mudie&#8217;s family, friends, and emergency services still working on the fire.</p>



<p class="">The tragedy comes just days&nbsp;<a href="https://www.ravensthorpe.wa.gov.au/news/message-of-condolence/711">after the death of former Shire President Keith Dunlop</a>, who served the community for many years including as president from 2015 to 2023.</p>



<p class="">Mr Dunlop was also deeply involved in emergency services and led the shire through natural disasters including floods and drought.</p>



<p class="">The loss of two respected community leaders in quick succession has left Ravensthorpe reeling.</p>



<p class="">The Western Australian Cricket Association is seeking a 10-year exemption from paying&nbsp;<strong>City of Perth</strong>&nbsp;rates, worth up to two-point-five million dollars,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.abc.net.au/news/2025-12-01/waca-seeks-total-exemption-from-paying-council-rates-until-2035/106088796">according to ABC News.</a></p>



<p class="">Council staff have recommended rejecting the application when it comes before councillors on December ninth.</p>



<p class="">The WACA has already benefited from one-point-eight-eight million dollars in rates exemptions since 2013, paying just 10 percent of levied amounts.</p>



<p class="">With the WACA Ground set to reopen after redevelopment, officers recommend a phased return to full rates by 2028.</p>



<p class=""><strong>NT</strong>:</p>



<p class=""><strong>Alice Springs Town Council</strong>&nbsp;has confirmed the Civic Centre site as&nbsp;<a href="https://www.alicesprings.nt.gov.au/residents/facilities/library/new-alice-springs-library-project.aspx">the location for a new 20-million-dollar purpose-built library</a>.</p>



<p class="">The current library has outgrown its nearly 40-year-old building, with patrons often sitting on floors during busy periods.</p>



<p class="">The Northern Territory Government is partnering with the council on the project.</p>



<p class="">Councillor Valda Napurrurla Shannon Warntaparri has been&nbsp;<a href="https://www.barkly.nt.gov.au/barkly-regional-council-announces-new-deputy-mayor">endorsed as the new Deputy Mayor</a>&nbsp;of&nbsp;<strong>Barkly Regional Council</strong>.</p>



<p class="">She&#8217;s a Warlpiri and Warumungu woman who previously developed suicide prevention programs and worked as an Aboriginal interpreter.</p>



<p class="">Outgoing Deputy Mayor Noel Hayes remains as an elected member.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Global Report</h2>



<p class="">NZ:</p>



<p class="">The New Zealand Government has announced plans to limit annual council rates increases to a maximum of 4% under a new regulatory model aimed at easing cost-of-living pressures on ratepayers.</p>



<p class="">Local Government Minister Simon Watts says the proposed system will establish a target range for rates increases, initially set between 2% and 4% per capita annually. The cap will apply from January 2027, with full regulatory implementation by July 2029.</p>



<p class="">Under the model, councils won&#8217;t be able to exceed the upper limit without permission from a government-appointed regulator. Exemptions will only be granted in extreme circumstances, such as natural disasters.</p>



<p class="">Mr Watts warns that officials will monitor rates rises nationwide once legislation is enacted next year, and councils proposing increases beyond the cap may face intervention under the Local Government Act.</p>



<p class="">The announcement has drawn mixed reactions. Local Government New Zealand&#8217;s interim chief executive Scott Necklen says the flexible approach is somewhat reassuring, but wants assurance the policy won&#8217;t affect councils&#8217; ability to invest in core infrastructure.</p>



<p class="">Opposition parties have criticised the proposal. Labour&#8217;s Tangi Utikere warns it will force councils to hike fees or cut services altogether, while the Greens&#8217; Celia Wade-Brown says capping rates does nothing to fix decades of infrastructure underinvestment.</p>



<p class="">Gisborne Mayor Rehette Stoltz notes that several councils are rebuilding infrastructure after severe weather events and need flexibility to deliver critical services in a timely way.</p>



<p class="">Targeted consultation with stakeholders begins today and runs through February 2026.</p>



<p class="">Mayors from Whanganui, Ruapehu, and Rangitīkei say the move was expected, but t<a href="https://www.nzherald.co.nz/whanganui-chronicle/news/rates-capping-govt-proposal-no-surprise-for-mayors-in-whanganui-ruapehu-and-rangitikei/33FKVBJH2VE4PPTMHTFUR3LQWY/">old the Whanganui Chronicle</a>&nbsp;they are concerned about maintaining essential infrastructure investment and service levels within these constraints.</p>



<p class="">Whanganui already has the country&#8217;s lowest rates rise at 2.2%, other some neighbouring councils have increases around 9% and face challenges reducing this to meet the proposed cap.</p>



<p class=""><em>More sources:</em></p>



<p class=""><a href="https://www.1news.co.nz/2025/12/01/govt-proposes-to-limit-council-rates-rises-to-4-in-new-system">1 News</a>;&nbsp;<a href="https://www.rnz.co.nz/news/political/580540/local-councils-relieved-with-government-s-rates-capping-approach">Radio New Zealand</a>;&nbsp;<a href="https://www.stuff.co.nz/politics/360905232/government-announces-rates-cap-keep-councils-within-their-means">Stuff</a></p>



<p class="">UK:</p>



<p class=""><strong>Rochdale Council</strong>&#8216;s chief executive, James Binks, has been suspended over allegations of inappropriate behaviour at&nbsp;<strong>Manchester City Council</strong>.</p>



<p class="">Council leader Neil Emmott announced the suspension on December 1st after an independent investigation substantiated a complaint. The complaint alleged that at last year&#8217;s Christmas event, Mr Binks was &#8220;inappropriately touching and grinding&#8221; against a junior female employee at the Dirty Martini bar.</p>



<p class="">The review found the atmosphere &#8220;sleazy&#8221; and &#8220;creepy.&#8221; HR director Mark Bennett witnessed the behaviour and intervened.</p>



<p class="">Councillor Emmott stated: &#8220;In light of these reports and the need to ensure that the reputation of the council is upheld, I have taken the decision to suspend James from work.&#8221;</p>



<p class="">Mr Binks, appointed to the £200,000 role in January, has apologised but denied any sexual element. Rochdale Council is following normal processes.</p>



<p class="">An acting chief executive will be confirmed while the monitoring officer examines the complaint.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Sources:</strong></p>



<p class=""><a href="https://www.rochdaletimes.co.uk/chief-executive-suspended-as-rochdale-council-investigates-complaint/">Rochdale Times &#8211; Chief executive suspended as Rochdale Council investigates complaint</a></p>



<p class=""><a href="https://www.manchestereveningnews.co.uk/news/council-chief-executive-suspended-over-32979724">Manchester Evening News &#8211; Council chief executive suspended over allegations of inappropriate behaviour</a></p>



<p class="">The Supreme Court has ruled that&nbsp;<strong>Epping Forest District Council</strong>&nbsp;cannot challenge the Home Office&#8217;s intervention in its failed bid to block asylum seekers from staying at the Bell Hotel.</p>



<p class="">The council had won an emergency injunction in August to close the hotel to migrants, but this was overturned by the Court of Appeal.</p>



<p class="">In November, the High Court dismissed the council&#8217;s claim that housing asylum seekers breached planning rules.</p>



<p class="">The council announced last month that it would appeal the High Court&#8217;s ruling,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/cn98171relno">according to BBC News.</a></p>



<p class="">CANADA:</p>



<p class="">In Canadian municipal news:</p>



<p class="">It has taken&nbsp;<strong>Saskatoon City Council</strong>&nbsp;<a href="https://www.ctvnews.ca/saskatoon/article/fourth-day-needed-to-finalize-city-budget/">four days of deliberations to finalise its budget</a>, methodically working through options to reduce spending. Among the tough decisions made &#8211; bus fares will increase for the first time in a decade, but a historic pool has been saved from closure.</p>



<p class="">Meanwhile in&nbsp;<strong>Edmonton</strong>, the council’s budget deliberations have just begun, with a 6.4 per cent property tax increase proposed to raise 2.28 billion dollars. But it needs 3.8 billion dollars to cover expenses as they stand.</p>



<p class="">The&nbsp;<strong>City of Calgary</strong>&nbsp;has become the first Canadian city&nbsp;<a href="https://www.ctvnews.ca/calgary/article/calgary-recertified-as-bird-friendly-city-for-third-time/">to be certified bird-friendly for the third time</a>&nbsp;by Nature Canada. The designation recognises municipalities that support birds throughout their life cycle, serving as an indicator of overall environmental health.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Roundup Extra:</strong></p>



<p class="">Anne-Marie Cade &#8211; conflict resolution expert and former mayor on how councils can navigate a challenging time post mayoral elections.</p>



<p class=""><a href="https://www.dianekalensukra.com/post/registration-open-civility-summit-2026">https://www.dianekalensukra.com/post/registration-open-civility-summit-2026</a></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://lgnewsroundup.com/rate-cap-breach-intervention-and-a-tragic-loss-ft-anne-marie-cade-524/">Rate cap breach, intervention and a tragic loss &#8211; ft.Anne-Marie Cade #524</a> appeared first on <a href="https://lgnewsroundup.com">Local Government News Roundup</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<post-id xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">6720</post-id>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Newsfeed &#8211; Tuesday, 2/12/25</title>
		<link>https://lgnewsroundup.com/newsfeed-tuesday-2-12-25/?utm_source=rss&#038;utm_medium=rss&#038;utm_campaign=newsfeed-tuesday-2-12-25</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[LG News Roundup]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 19:43:24 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[International]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[QLD]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Victoria]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://lgnewsroundup.com/?p=6710</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>A second Victorian Council in breach of the rate capNew Yarra Ranges advocacy platform releasedNew guidelines for renewable energy projects: MurrindindiUK Council CEO suspendedMurrundindi survey shows concern for proposed health mergerQLD Govt appoints adviser to Redland Council VIC: Alpine Shire Council&#160;has confirmed the breach, blaming it on a system error that led to rates being [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://lgnewsroundup.com/newsfeed-tuesday-2-12-25/">Newsfeed &#8211; Tuesday, 2/12/25</a> appeared first on <a href="https://lgnewsroundup.com">Local Government News Roundup</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p class=""><a href="#alpine">A second Victorian Council in breach of the rate cap</a><br><a href="#yarra-ranges">New Yarra Ranges advocacy platform released</a><br><a href="#guidelines">New guidelines for renewable energy projects: Murrindindi</a><br><a href="#rochdale">UK Council CEO suspended</a><br><a href="#murrundindi">Murrundindi survey shows concern for proposed health merger</a><br><a href="#redland">QLD Govt appoints adviser to Redland Council</a></p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<p id="alpine" class="">VIC: <strong>Alpine Shire Council</strong>&nbsp;<a href="https://www.alpineshire.vic.gov.au/news/council-taking-steps-rectify-202526-rate-cap-breach">has confirmed the breach</a>, blaming it on a system error that led to rates being calculated incorrectly.</p>



<p class="">The error resulted in an average rate increase of 3.96% instead of the mandated 3% cap, collecting an extra $168,304 from ratepayers.</p>



<p class="">The mistake occurred when a rating system provider applied a classification change earlier than advised, throwing off the base rate calculations.</p>



<p class="">Council CEO Will Jeremy said there was no intention to exceed the cap, and there&#8217;s no penalty or fine for the breach.</p>



<p class="">The Council will consider how to rectify the breach at its December.</p>



<p class="">It is likely that it will adjust next year&#8217;s rates to be at least $168,304 lower than they would otherwise be.</p>



<p class="">The breach is one of two reported by the Essential Services Commission in its report on the rate cap &#8211; in September this year, <strong>Hindmarsh Shire Council</strong> <a href="https://www.hindmarsh.vic.gov.au/Council/News-and-Media/Latest-News/20252026-Rate-Cap-Calculation">admitted to an error</a> that saw it raise nearly $4,000 above the cap.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<p id="yarra-ranges" class="">VIC: <strong>Yarra Ranges Council</strong>&nbsp;has endorsed&nbsp;<a href="https://www.yarraranges.vic.gov.au/Our-Council/Latest-news/Council-sets-advocacy-priorities-for-2025-27">a new advocacy platform</a>&nbsp;to guide its conversations with State and Federal Governments ahead of the 2026 State Election.</p>



<p class="">The priorities include safe road crossings on state-managed roads, more affordable housing, additional funding for the Yarra Valley Trail, and better public transport.</p>



<p class="">Mayor Richard Higgins says the platform reflects community feedback and expert analysis.</p>



<p class="">Key asks include funding for a new aquatics facility to replace the closed Kilsyth Pool and pedestrian crossings along the Warburton Highway.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<p id="guidelines" class="">VIC: <strong>Murrindindi Shire Council</strong>&nbsp;has released draft&nbsp;<a href="https://www.murrindindi.vic.gov.au/Council/News-and-Media/Council-News/Murrindindi-Shire-leads-the-way-with-draft-guidelines-for-renewable-energy-development">guidelines for renewable energy development</a>, open for community feedback until February 8, 2026.</p>



<p class="">The guidelines respond to growing concern about large-scale energy projects and their impact on farming, tourism, and the local landscape.</p>



<p class="">Deputy Mayor Anita Carr says the framework puts community values first, demanding genuine engagement, transparency, and tangible local benefits from developers.</p>



<p class="">The guidelines emphasise protection of significant landscapes, partnership with Traditional Owners, and clear criteria for project siting and decommissioning.</p>



<p class="">Council is urging all residents to review the draft and share their views on The Loop, their online engagement platform.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<p id="rochdale" class="">UK: <strong>Rochdale Council</strong>&#8216;s chief executive, James Binks, has been suspended over allegations of inappropriate behaviour at&nbsp;<strong>Manchester City Council</strong>.</p>



<p class="">Council leader Neil Emmott <a href="https://www.rochvalleyradio.com/news/local-news/rochdale-council-leader-neil-emmott-provides-update-on-suspended-chief-exec/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">announced the suspension on December 1st</a> after an independent investigation substantiated a complaint. The complaint alleged that at last year&#8217;s Christmas event, Mr Binks was &#8220;inappropriately touching and grinding&#8221; against a junior female employee at the Dirty Martini bar.</p>



<p class="">The review found the atmosphere &#8220;sleazy&#8221; and &#8220;creepy.&#8221; HR director Mark Bennett witnessed the behaviour and intervened.</p>



<p class="">Councillor Emmott stated: &#8220;In light of these reports and the need to ensure that the reputation of the council is upheld, I have taken the decision to suspend James from work.&#8221;</p>



<p class="">Mr Binks, appointed to the £200,000 role in January, has apologised but denied any sexual element. Rochdale Council is following normal processes.</p>



<p class="">An acting chief executive will be confirmed while the monitoring officer examines the complaint.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Sources:</strong><br><a href="https://www.rochdaletimes.co.uk/chief-executive-suspended-as-rochdale-council-investigates-complaint/">Rochdale Times &#8211; Chief executive suspended as Rochdale Council investigates complaint</a><br><a href="https://www.manchestereveningnews.co.uk/news/council-chief-executive-suspended-over-32979724">Manchester Evening News &#8211; Council chief executive suspended over allegations of inappropriate behaviour</a></p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<p id="redland" class="">QLD: A governance adviser has been appointed to&nbsp;<strong>Redland City Council</strong>&nbsp;after it led Queensland with 114 councillor complaints in the last financial year.</p>



<p class="">Mayor Jos Mitchell has received at least 47 complaints since taking office in 2024, though she claims the anonymous system has been weaponised against her,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.brisbanetimes.com.au/national/queensland/governance-adviser-appointed-for-complaint-plagued-bayside-council-20251201-p5njxe.html">according to the Brisbane Times.</a></p>



<p class="">The adviser will work with the council until May, focusing on leadership, communication, and councillor conduct.</p>



<p class="">Mayor Mitchell is also locked in a defamation lawsuit with the council&#8217;s top legal officer.</p>



<p class="">The intervention follows calls from the mayor herself for external support. The identity of the adviser is yet to be announced.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<p id="murrundindi" class="">VIC: <strong>Murrindindi Shire Council</strong>&nbsp;has released&nbsp;<a href="https://www.murrindindi.vic.gov.au/Council/News-and-Media/Council-News/Council-releases-community-healthcare-survey-results">survey results on a proposed health service merger.</a></p>



<p class="">The 16-day survey attracted 278 responses about the voluntary amalgamation between Alexandra District Health and Eastern Health.</p>



<p class="">Most respondents expressed concern about potential impacts on local services and decision-making.</p>



<p class="">A smaller group supported the proposal, citing possible benefits like improved specialist access.</p>



<p class="">Mayor Damien Gallagher said the results reinforce the importance of ensuring the community is fully informed and actively involved.</p>



<p class="">He said the Council will share the results with both health boards to inform their decision-making.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://lgnewsroundup.com/newsfeed-tuesday-2-12-25/">Newsfeed &#8211; Tuesday, 2/12/25</a> appeared first on <a href="https://lgnewsroundup.com">Local Government News Roundup</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<post-id xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">6710</post-id>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Newsfeed &#8211; Monday, 1/12/25</title>
		<link>https://lgnewsroundup.com/newsfeed-monday-1-12-25/?utm_source=rss&#038;utm_medium=rss&#038;utm_campaign=newsfeed-monday-1-12-25</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[LG News Roundup]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 23:43:28 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[NSW]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[QLD]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Victoria]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://lgnewsroundup.com/?p=6691</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>NZ Government proposes 4% cap on council rates increasesHume Council action results in VCAT orders against illegal earthworksNth Grampians to review community care servicesHistoric Lambton dive tower closed over safety concernsBendigo launches new emergency dashboardLarge scale event approval for Marrickville clubNew Coonamble Shire GM starts workMoreton Bay platypus project reveals surprising resultsHepburn Shire approves sale [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://lgnewsroundup.com/newsfeed-monday-1-12-25/">Newsfeed &#8211; Monday, 1/12/25</a> appeared first on <a href="https://lgnewsroundup.com">Local Government News Roundup</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p class=""><a href="#nz-ratecap">NZ Government proposes 4% cap on council rates increases</a><br><a href="#hume">Hume Council action results in VCAT orders against illegal earthworks</a><br><a href="#agedcare">Nth Grampians to review community care services</a><br><a href="#lambton">Historic Lambton dive tower closed over safety concerns</a><br><a href="#bendigo">Bendigo launches new emergency dashboard</a><br><a href="#inner-west">Large scale event approval for Marrickville club</a><br><a href="#coonamble">New Coonamble Shire GM starts work</a><br><a href="#platypus">Moreton Bay platypus project reveals surprising results</a><br><a href="#hepburn">Hepburn Shire approves sale of surplus properties</a></p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<p id="nz-ratecap" class="">NZ: The New Zealand Government has announced plans to limit annual council rates increases to a maximum of 4% under a new regulatory model aimed at easing cost-of-living pressures on ratepayers.</p>



<p class="">Local Government Minister Simon Watts says the proposed system will establish a target range for rates increases, initially set between 2% and 4% per capita annually. The cap will apply from January 2027, with full regulatory implementation by July 2029.</p>



<p class="">Under the model, councils won&#8217;t be able to exceed the upper limit without permission from a government-appointed regulator. Exemptions will only be granted in extreme circumstances, such as natural disasters.</p>



<p class="">Watts warns that officials will monitor rates rises nationwide once legislation is enacted next year, and councils proposing increases beyond the cap may face intervention under the Local Government Act.</p>



<p class="">The announcement has drawn mixed reactions. Local Government New Zealand&#8217;s interim chief executive Scott Necklen says the flexible approach is somewhat reassuring, but wants assurance the policy won&#8217;t affect councils&#8217; ability to invest in core infrastructure.</p>



<p class="">Opposition parties have criticised the proposal. Labour&#8217;s Tangi Utikere warns it will force councils to hike fees or cut services altogether, while the Greens&#8217; Celia Wade-Brown says capping rates does nothing to fix decades of infrastructure underinvestment.</p>



<p class="">Gisborne Mayor Rehette Stoltz notes that several councils are rebuilding infrastructure after severe weather events and need flexibility to deliver critical services in a timely way.</p>



<p class="">Targeted consultation with stakeholders begins today and runs through February 2026.</p>



<p class=""><em>Sources:</em><br><a href="https://www.1news.co.nz/2025/12/01/govt-proposes-to-limit-council-rates-rises-to-4-in-new-system" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">1 News</a>; <a href="https://www.rnz.co.nz/news/political/580540/local-councils-relieved-with-government-s-rates-capping-approach" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Radio New Zealand</a>; <a href="https://www.stuff.co.nz/politics/360905232/government-announces-rates-cap-keep-councils-within-their-means" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Stuff</a></p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<p id="hume" class="">VIC: The Victorian Civil and Administrative Tribunal has issued&nbsp;<a href="https://www.hume.vic.gov.au/Residents/Latest-News/News-and-Media-Releases/2025/VCAT-orders-halt-illegal-earthworks-on-Sunbury-properties">enforcement orders stopping illegal earthworks</a>&nbsp;on three Sunbury properties.</p>



<p class="">The orders follow&nbsp;<strong>Hume City Council</strong>&nbsp;action over works that breached planning rules designed to protect the environment.</p>



<p class="">No further earthworks can proceed without council approval or a planning permit.</p>



<p class="">Council will monitor the sites to ensure compliance and thanked residents for their vigilance.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<p id="agedcare" class="">VIC: <strong>Northern Grampians Shire Council</strong>&nbsp;will&nbsp;<a href="https://www.ngshire.vic.gov.au/Latest-News/News-Directory/Council-to-review-community-care-services">review its community care services</a>&nbsp;in light of major federal aged care reforms.</p>



<p class="">The new Aged Care Act shifts funding from block grants to fee-for-service models, allowing clients to choose their own providers, and CEO Brent McAlister says the council must determine whether to remain a service provider or shift to advocacy and navigation roles.</p>



<p class="">Community engagement will begin in January with surveys and workshops in Stawell and St Arnaud.</p>



<p class="">No decisions have been made yet, and the council emphasises this is a genuine consultation process.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<p id="lambton" class="">NSW: The historic dive tower at Lambton Park War Memorial Swimming Centre&nbsp;<a href="https://newcastle.nsw.gov.au/about-us/news-and-updates/latest-news/media-statement-%E2%80%93-lambton-park-war-memorial-swimming-centre-dive-tower">has been temporarily closed</a>&nbsp;following safety concerns raised by SafeWork NSW with the&nbsp;<strong>City of Newcastle</strong>.</p>



<p class="">Built in 1963, the tower is one of only two heritage diving facilities still operating in Australia. SafeWork inspections identified fall and slip risks on the tower and springboards.</p>



<p class="">The city is now conducting a risk assessment and consulting with the local dive club&#8217;s 70 members about the facility&#8217;s future.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<p id="bendigo" class="">VIC: The&nbsp;<strong>City of Greater Bendigo</strong>&nbsp;has unveiled&nbsp;<a href="https://www.bendigo.vic.gov.au/about-us/news-and-media/city-launches-new-emergency-dashboard-help-residents-stay-safe">a new Emergency Dashboard on its website</a>&nbsp;to help residents access critical information during bushfires, floods, and other emergencies.</p>



<p class="">The dashboard features real-time warnings, weather updates, road closures, and relief centre locations, all in one mobile-friendly platform.</p>



<p class="">It draws information from trusted sources including VicEmergency, SES, and CFA.</p>



<p class="">The City has also released new &#8216;What&#8217;s Your Plan?&#8217; guides to help families and businesses prepare emergency plans and kits.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<p id="inner-west" class="">NSW: The Sydney Portugal Community Club in Marrickville has been approved by&nbsp;<strong>Inner West Council</strong>&nbsp;<a href="https://www.innerwest.nsw.gov.au/about/news/media-releases/2025-media-releases/large-scale-events-sydney-portugal-community-club">to host large-scale outdoor events.</a></p>



<p class="">The club can now hold five events with up to 5,000 patrons and ten smaller events with up to 3,500 patrons annually.</p>



<p class="">Mayor Darcy Byrne says it will strengthen the Inner West&#8217;s position as Sydney&#8217;s live music and entertainment hub.</p>



<p class="">The club aims to celebrate Portuguese culture while contributing to Marrickville&#8217;s diverse community.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><img decoding="async" width="580" height="603" src="https://i0.wp.com/lgnewsroundup.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/592294022_1436310265162667_1467554169668938829_n.jpeg?fit=580%2C603&amp;ssl=1" alt="" class="wp-image-6696" style="width:229px;height:auto" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/lgnewsroundup.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/592294022_1436310265162667_1467554169668938829_n.jpeg?w=580&amp;ssl=1 580w, https://i0.wp.com/lgnewsroundup.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/592294022_1436310265162667_1467554169668938829_n.jpeg?resize=289%2C300&amp;ssl=1 289w" sizes="(max-width: 580px) 100vw, 580px" /></figure>
</div>


<p id="coonamble" class="">NSW: Greg Hill has commenced his new role as General Manager of <strong>Coonamble Shire Council</strong>, moving from his previous role at<strong> Central Darling Shire</strong>. </p>



<p class="">Mayor Daniel Keady <a href="https://www.facebook.com/share/p/1AHUtT7N1b/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">welcomed Mr Hill to the council today</a>, and thanked outgoing Interim General Manager Phillip Perram for his contribution to the shire in recent months.</p>



<p class=""></p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<p id="platypus" class="">QLD: An innovative platypus monitoring project has revealed the platypus population in <strong>City of Moreton Bay</strong> is more widespread than initially thought.</p>



<p class="">The project <a href="https://www.moretonbay.qld.gov.au/News/Media/Platypus-population-paddling-strongly-in-City-of-Moreton-Bay" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">has confirmed the presence of platypus</a> – a species known for its elusive behaviour – in at least 37 creeks and rivers across the City. </p>



<p class="">It even positively detected platypus DNA in Conflagration Creek at a major industrial area.</p>



<p class="">The project – now in its third year &#8211; will help Council to safeguard platypus habitat though proactive management of the species and their environment to aid long-term survival.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="864" height="358" src="https://i0.wp.com/lgnewsroundup.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/A-platypus-in-the-South-Pine-River-below-the-Kumbartcho-Environmental-Centre.-Credit-Bruce-Duffy.jpg?fit=864%2C358&amp;ssl=1" alt="" class="wp-image-6693" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/lgnewsroundup.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/A-platypus-in-the-South-Pine-River-below-the-Kumbartcho-Environmental-Centre.-Credit-Bruce-Duffy.jpg?w=864&amp;ssl=1 864w, https://i0.wp.com/lgnewsroundup.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/A-platypus-in-the-South-Pine-River-below-the-Kumbartcho-Environmental-Centre.-Credit-Bruce-Duffy.jpg?resize=300%2C124&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/lgnewsroundup.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/A-platypus-in-the-South-Pine-River-below-the-Kumbartcho-Environmental-Centre.-Credit-Bruce-Duffy.jpg?resize=768%2C318&amp;ssl=1 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><em><sup>Image credit: Bruce Duffy</sup></em></figcaption></figure>
</div>


<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<p id="hepburn" class="">VIC: <strong>Hepburn Shire Council</strong>&nbsp;has&nbsp;<a href="https://www.hepburn.vic.gov.au/Council/News/Latest-news/Surplus-Council-land-sale-approved-with-safeguards-for-Rea-Lands-Park">approved the sale of seven surplus properties</a>, five of which have been earmarked for affordable housing development.</p>



<p class="">The decision follows community consultation that began in July 2025.</p>



<p class="">Proceeds from the sales will fund a financial reserve to support future grant applications.</p>



<p class="">Rea Lands Reserve in Daylesford will remain a public park after significant community feedback in support of its retention.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://lgnewsroundup.com/newsfeed-monday-1-12-25/">Newsfeed &#8211; Monday, 1/12/25</a> appeared first on <a href="https://lgnewsroundup.com">Local Government News Roundup</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<post-id xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">6691</post-id>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Overwhelming demerger vote, city turmoil, and &#8220;concerning misrepresentation&#8221; &#8211; #523</title>
		<link>https://lgnewsroundup.com/overwhelming-demerger-vote-city-turmoil-and-concerning-misrepresentation-523/?utm_source=rss&#038;utm_medium=rss&#038;utm_campaign=overwhelming-demerger-vote-city-turmoil-and-concerning-misrepresentation-523</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[LG News Roundup]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 20:49:11 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[New episode]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[International]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[NSW]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[QLD]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[South Australia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tasmania]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Victoria]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Western Australia]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://lgnewsroundup.com/?p=6685</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Today on the Local Government News Roundup: The Local Government News Roundup is brought to you by the&#160;Victorian Local Governance Association, the national broadcaster on all things local government; with support from Symphony3 &#8211; simple, connected customer experiences. Listen to the episode here. Read along with all the news from this episode below: Victorian Report [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://lgnewsroundup.com/overwhelming-demerger-vote-city-turmoil-and-concerning-misrepresentation-523/">Overwhelming demerger vote, city turmoil, and &#8220;concerning misrepresentation&#8221; &#8211; #523</a> appeared first on <a href="https://lgnewsroundup.com">Local Government News Roundup</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p class="">Today on the Local Government News Roundup:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li class="">Councils get behind a global campaign to end gender-based violence</li>



<li class="">A disappointing decision to close a community pool</li>



<li class="">A referendum returns an overwhelming vote for deamalgamation of Snowy Valleys Council</li>



<li class="">Newcastle’s Deputy Lord Mayor cops criticism from a local MP</li>



<li class="">A council offers a $10,000 reward following a tree vandalism incident</li>



<li class="">A mayor’s decision to go to the Winter Olympics under fire</li>



<li class="">A Tasmanian mayor survives an attempted no-confidence motion</li>



<li class="">Turmoil at the City of Perth as its Acting CEO resigns, and</li>



<li class="">The shire that wants to be a city</li>
</ul>



<p class="">The Local Government News Roundup is brought to you by the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.vlga.org.au/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Victorian Local Governance Association</a>, the national broadcaster on all things local government; with support from <a href="http://www.symphony3.com">Symphony3</a> &#8211; simple, connected customer experiences.</p>



<p class=""><a href="https://www.buzzsprout.com/1726495/episodes/18274641-overwhelming-demerger-vote-city-turmoil-and-concerning-misrepresentation-523" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Listen to the episode here.</a></p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<p class="">Read along with all the news from this episode below:</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Victorian Report</h2>



<p class="">Local governments across the country are taking part in a global campaign to end violence against women which is now underway.</p>



<p class="">The 16 Days of Activism against Gender-Based Violence campaign commenced last week and runs through December 10.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Hobsons Bay City Council</strong>&nbsp;is using the campaign&nbsp;<a href="https://www.hobsonsbay.vic.gov.au/News-Media/2025/November/Greater-action-called-for-as-16-Days-of-Activism-gets-under-way">to demand greater state government action</a>&nbsp;as family violence incidents in the municipality surged 12 percent last year.</p>



<p class="">Emergency department presentations are up 56 percent in two years.</p>



<p class="">Mayor Diana Grima and community partners have written to state ministers and local MPs calling for more crisis accommodation, mental health services, and affordable housing.</p>



<p class="">The Altona Theatre will be lit orange throughout the campaign.</p>



<p class="">Peak body, the MAV, is&nbsp;<a href="https://safeandequal.org.au/16-days-of-activism-against-gender-based-violence-2025/">supporting Safe and Equal</a>, who are leading Respect Victoria’s campaign this year.</p>



<p class="">The closure of the Port Fairy pool and fitness centre&nbsp;<a href="https://www.moyne.vic.gov.au/News-and-media/belfast-aquatics">is now confirmed to be permanent,</a>&nbsp;after its recent shut down due to the discovery of mould in the building.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Moyne Shire Council</strong>, and leaseholder Belfast Aquatics, have confirmed a cost of more than $2M to save the facility.</p>



<p class="">The current lease expired yesterday, and the council says it has no plans for the facility to continue operating.</p>



<p class="">Mayor Jordan Lockett acknowledged the impact of the decision on the community, and the disappointment of many residents.</p>



<p class="">He said the council is developing an aquatic facilities strategy to inform future investment and service provision in community pools, which is expected to come before the Council by next June.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Cardinia Shire Council</strong>&nbsp;has announced that the Pakenham Outdoor Pool&nbsp;<a href="https://www.cardinia.vic.gov.au/news/article/1546/update_on_pakenham_outdoor_pool_works">won&#8217;t reopen this summer</a>&nbsp;due to weather-related construction delays.</p>



<p class="">Essential upgrade works including structural repairs, resealing, and new fencing require dry conditions to complete properly.</p>



<p class="">The Council says it is prioritising quality over speed to deliver improved facilities.</p>



<p class="">The upgraded facility is expected to reopen for the 2026-27 summer season.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Melton City Council</strong>&nbsp;is pushing the Victorian government to fast-track electrification of the Melton rail line.</p>



<p class=""><a href="https://meltonmoorabool.starweekly.com.au/news/council-urges-fast-track-for-melton-line/">The Star Weekly reported</a>&nbsp;that the council wants full funding committed, including new stations at Thornhill Park and Mount Atkinson.</p>



<p class="">The state government says rebuilding Sunshine Station is the first step toward electrification.</p>



<p class="">The council is calling for a transparent timeline and delivery alongside the Sunshine Super Hub upgrade.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Darebin City Council</strong>&nbsp;has&nbsp;<a href="https://www.youtube.com/live/RDY9MV8lnQE">deferred a decision on a memorial</a>&nbsp;for late councillor Gaetano Greco until next year.</p>



<p class="">The Council&nbsp;<a href="https://www.darebin.vic.gov.au/files/assets/public/v/1/about-council/documents/council-meetings/2025/24-november-2025/addendum-to-agenda-item-9.7-darebin-council-memorial-to-cr-gaetano-greco.pdf">received a report at its meeting last week</a>&nbsp;canvassing various options for a memorial, including the naming of a park, a cultural centre or an appropriate artwork.</p>



<p class="">The Mayor Emily Dimitriadis and Cr Angela Villella will lead consultation with former Cr Greco’s family, before a further report comes back to the Council in March.</p>



<p class="">Former&nbsp;<strong>Macedon Ranges Shire</strong>&nbsp;mayor Dominic Bonnano is taking a six month leave of absence, in the wake of a recent speeding and drink driving incident in the mayoral vehicle.</p>



<p class="">The leave of absence will go through til late May, during which time he will not receive a councillor allowance.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Stonnington</strong>&nbsp;councillors are seeking an extension of time to receive a report from an animal management taskforce which has been looking at options for the future provision of animal management and welfare services in the city.</p>



<p class="">A potential regional pound and in-house delivery options are part of the review.</p>



<p class="">The extension request will be considered by the Council at its 1st December meeting.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Glen Eira City Council</strong>&nbsp;has resolved to&nbsp;<a href="https://www.gleneira.vic.gov.au/media/k2odqxxm/co_25112025_min_1372.pdf">develop a stand-alone two-year anti-semitism strategy.</a></p>



<p class="">The strategy will be informed by best practice models and community consultation, as a short-term response and foundation for a future social cohesion strategy.</p>



<p class="">The council will also monitor antisemitism trends on an ongoing basis, and advocate for additional resources and partnerships to strengthen community resilience.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Loddon Shire Council</strong>&nbsp;is revising its advocacy priorities ahead of the 2026 Victorian Election.</p>



<p class="">Childcare access will now be prioritised across the entire shire, not just the northern region.</p>



<p class="">Mayor Dan Straub says the update ensures leaders know what matters most to local communities.</p>



<p class="">The Council advocates for fair childcare access but doesn&#8217;t provide or control these services.</p>



<p class="">The last priorities update was done before the 2025 Federal Election</p>



<p class=""><strong>Latrobe City Council</strong>&nbsp;is tackling CBD anti-social behaviour with new outreach program.</p>



<p class="">The Council has allocated thirty thousand dollars to develop a community outreach model connecting vulnerable people with support services.</p>



<p class="">The initiative will focus on high-traffic areas like CBDs and transport hubs, using trained staff to de-escalate situations.</p>



<p class="">The Council says the move addresses retailer and community concerns about safety, and comes after the State Government failed to provide requested support including more Protective Service Officers.</p>



<p class="">The&nbsp;<strong>City of Greater Bendigo</strong>&nbsp;<a href="https://www.bendigo.vic.gov.au/about-us/news-and-media/city-scoops-gold-victorian-tourism-awards">won Gold at the 2025 Victorian Tourism Awards</a>&nbsp;in the Local Government Award for Tourism category, marking its sixth consecutive year as a finalist with four gold and two silver awards achieved during this period.</p>



<p class="">The&nbsp;<strong>Greater Shepparton</strong>&nbsp;Visitor Centre has&nbsp;<a href="https://greatershepparton.com.au/whats-happening/news/news-article/!/456/post/greater-shepparton-visitor-centre-awarded-silver-at-the-2025-victorian-tourism-awards">won silver in the Visitor Information Servicing category</a>.</p>



<p class="">The award recognises innovative initiatives including the TAC Pause Stop program, and support for major events like GT Nationals.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Victorian Briefs</h2>



<p class=""><strong>Cardinia Shire Council</strong>&nbsp;will reduce its meetings to once a month starting in February, integrating town planning matters into general meetings and starting an hour earlier at 6pm.</p>



<p class="">The new schedule was adopted at the council’s Annual Meeting last week.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Colac Otway Shire</strong>&nbsp;is inviting mobile food vendors with unique, creative menus&nbsp;<a href="https://www.colacotway.vic.gov.au/News-media/Summer-Food-Truck-Trial">to participate in a Summer Food Truck Trial</a>&nbsp;from December to April at Lake Colac Foreshore and Memorial Square.</p>



<p class="">Applications must be submitted by Friday 12 December 2025.</p>



<p class="">The&nbsp;<strong>City of Greater Bendigo</strong>&nbsp;has become the first regional council and third in Australia to&nbsp;<a href="https://www.bendigo.vic.gov.au/about-us/news-and-media/greater-bendigo-recognised-excelling-welcoming-city">achieve Welcoming Cities Accreditation at the Excelling Level</a>&nbsp;under new national standards.</p>



<p class="">The accreditation recognises the city’s commitment to cultural diversity, Aboriginal reconciliation, and social cohesion, and strengthens its reputation as a national leader in inclusion.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="667" height="577" src="https://i0.wp.com/lgnewsroundup.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/2511-RCA-Deputy-Chair-Cr-Cherry-and-Chair-Cr-Black-v2.jpeg?fit=667%2C577&amp;ssl=1" alt="" class="wp-image-6688" style="width:226px;height:auto" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/lgnewsroundup.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/2511-RCA-Deputy-Chair-Cr-Cherry-and-Chair-Cr-Black-v2.jpeg?w=667&amp;ssl=1 667w, https://i0.wp.com/lgnewsroundup.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/2511-RCA-Deputy-Chair-Cr-Cherry-and-Chair-Cr-Black-v2.jpeg?resize=300%2C260&amp;ssl=1 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /></figure>
</div>


<p class=""><strong>Regional Capitals Australia</strong>&nbsp;has appointed&nbsp;<strong>Dubbo Regional Council</strong>&nbsp;Mayor Josh Black as its new Chair, with&nbsp;<strong>Tweed Shire Council</strong>&nbsp;Mayor Chris Cherry as Deputy Chair.</p>



<p class="">The organisation&nbsp;<a href="https://www.regionalcapitalsaustralia.org/">represents nine million Australians</a>&nbsp;living in or relying on regional capitals.</p>



<p class="">Cr Black outlines the group’s priorities for the coming months: </p>



<figure class="wp-block-audio"><audio controls src="https://lgnewsroundup.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/Josh-Black-grab.mp3"></audio></figure>



<p class="">Cr Black takes over from Peter Carter, who resigned in August, and acting Chair Kevin Mack.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">NSW Report</h2>



<p class="">A referendum on the future of&nbsp;<strong>Snowy Valleys Regional Council</strong>&nbsp;has returned&nbsp;<a href="https://results.elections.nsw.gov.au/LB2520/Snowy_Valleys/Referendum/FirstPreferencesReport.html">an overwhelming YES vote for de-amalgamation.</a></p>



<p class="">By the close of counting on Saturday night, more than 87% of votes were in favour of returning the amalgamated council to two separate entities based on the boundaries of the former Tumbarumba and Tumut Councils.</p>



<p class="">The two shires were involuntarily joined in 2016.</p>



<p class="">The Border Mail this morning reports on reaction to the result.</p>



<p class="">Snowy Valleys Mayor Julia Ham said there was still “red hot fury” felt by residents over the merger, and that was reflected in the referendum result.</p>



<p class="">Former Tumbarumba and Snowy Valleys Mayor Ian Chaffey said it was a clear message that rural Australians didn’t like being dictated to by the urban component of our society.</p>



<p class="">Once a final result is confirmed, the issue will go to the Minister for Local Government to determine the next steps. A demerger is estimated to cost nearly $5M and will take at least two years.</p>



<p class="">MP Tim Crakanthorp has criticised the&nbsp;<strong>City of Newcastle</strong>’s deputy lord mayor Charlotte McCabe after she postponed debate on ongoing safety issues in Beaumont Street until December.</p>



<p class=""><a href="https://www.newcastleherald.com.au/story/9121308/newcastle-mp-criticises-council-delay-on-beaumont-st-issues/">The Newcastle Herald reports</a>&nbsp;that the Hamilton precinct has been plagued by antisocial behaviour, including used needles and human waste.</p>



<p class="">Cr McCabe defended her decision, saying the late item, circulated on the day of the November meeting, didn&#8217;t meet urgency requirements under meeting rules.</p>



<p class="">Meanwhile, business owners and residents say the problems demand immediate action.</p>



<p class="">Mr Crakanthorp called the deferral &#8220;disappointing and simply not good enough&#8221;, while Cr McCabe said in a statement posted on her Facebook page that there had been &#8220;concerning misrepresentation&#8221; about the decision she made as the chair.</p>



<p class="">Cr McCabe is currently acting as Lord Mayor, while Ross Kerridge is on a leave of absence until February while he undergoes treatment for cancer.</p>



<p class=""><a href="https://au.news.yahoo.com/10000-reward-offered-as-aussie-council-hunts-culprit-of-shameful-act-030604880.html">Yahoo News reports</a>&nbsp;that a Sydney council is offering a ten-thousand-dollar reward after two red bottle brush trees were deliberately poisoned near Manly Beach.</p>



<p class="">The trees, which once brightened Reddall Street, now stand brown and dead, allegedly targeted to improve ocean views.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Northern Beaches Council</strong>&nbsp;has erected warning signs and is urging anyone with information to come forward.</p>



<p class="">The council said it takes the vandalism very seriously and is conducting a full investigation.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Upper Hunter Shire Council</strong>&nbsp;has slammed the revised transmission line route for the New England Renewable Energy Zone,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.upperhunter.nsw.gov.au/News/Council-Meeting-Recap-24-November-2025">calling community consultation inadequate.</a></p>



<p class="">Mayor Maurice Collison says the route cuts through productive farmland and passes over 18 homes, contradicting EnergyCo&#8217;s own guidelines to avoid clusters of homes and agricultural land.</p>



<p class="">The Council will write to EnergyCo and NSW Energy Minister Penny Sharpe demanding investigation into using existing transmission corridors.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Kempsey Shire Council</strong>&nbsp;has held a roundtable with NSW Government agencies and local services to&nbsp;<a href="https://www.kempsey.nsw.gov.au/Your-Council/Council-news-public-notices/Council-news-updates/20251128-MR-Social-Response">address homelessness and social issues</a>&nbsp;in the area.</p>



<p class="">Key barriers identified include inadequate funding and a shortage of affordable housing.</p>



<p class="">Council CEO Andrew Meddle says they&#8217;re committed to supporting lead agencies while respecting the dignity of every individual.</p>



<p class="">Illegal camping at Forth Street is being addressed, with fencing to be installed once occupants are relocated.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Port Macquarie Hastings Council</strong>&nbsp;is urging residents to report unsafe e-bike and e-scooter riding directly to state authorities.</p>



<p class=""><a href="https://portmacquarie.newsofthearea.com.au/council-urges-locals-to-report-unsafe-e-bike-and-e-scooter-riding">News of the Area reported</a>&nbsp;that concerns have been raised about dangerous riding in the town centre, particularly around the Town Green and Southern Breakwall.</p>



<p class="">Emergency data shows a 627 percent increase in e-bike injuries since 2019, with four child fatalities recorded since July.</p>



<p class="">The council will publish clear information on its website about reporting procedures and regulatory responsibilities.</p>



<p class="">Meanwhile, Transport for NSW has decided to&nbsp;<a href="https://www.pmhc.nsw.gov.au/Your-Council/News-Notices/News-articles/2025/November/Message-from-the-Mayor-Port-Macquarie-Southern-Breakwall-project">repair rather than replace the Port Macquarie Southern Breakwall</a>, ending the long-standing debate about full replacement.</p>



<p class="">Mayor Adam Roberts aid the news will come as welcome relief to many in the community, and has offered support for a potential new project to widen the breakwall footpath to accommodate increasing pedestrian traffic.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">NSW Briefs:</h2>



<p class="">The NSW Government has awarded funding to&nbsp;<strong>Shoalhaven City Council</strong>&nbsp;<a href="https://www.shoalhaven.nsw.gov.au/News-and-feedback/News-and-media/News/Council-welcomes-funding-for-new-EV-charging-stations">to install electric vehicle charging infrastructure</a>&nbsp;at two public sites in Vincentia and Ulladulla.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Dungog Shire Council</strong>&nbsp;has opened consultation&nbsp;<a href="https://www.dungog.nsw.gov.au/Projects-Works/Other-works/Housing-and-Infrastructure-Master-Plan">on a suite of strategic planning documents</a>, to address housing, infrastructure and environment needs over the next 15 years.</p>



<p class="">The documents include a local housing strategy for delivering a minimum 2,400 new homes by 2041. Consultation is open until 21st December.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Ballina Shire Council</strong>&nbsp;is set to&nbsp;<a href="https://www.ballina.nsw.gov.au/Council/News-Careers-and-Feedback/Media-Releases/Major-safety-and-access-upgrade-for-Ballina%E2%80%99s-critical-evacuation-routes">duplicate two critical bridges to improve evacuation routes</a>&nbsp;and ease congestion.</p>



<p class="">The Fishery Creek Bridge on River Street and Canal Bridge on Tamarind Drive will be expanded to four lanes each. Construction is expected to begin in February and finish in the second half of 2027, backed by 40 million dollars from the Australian Government&#8217;s Emergency Response Fund.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Queensland Report</h2>



<p class=""><strong>Gold Coast</strong>&nbsp;Mayor Tom Tate will bill ratepayers for a trip to Italy to carry the Winter Olympics torch in late January and February.</p>



<p class=""><a href="https://www.goldcoastbulletin.com.au/news/council/gold-coast-mayor-and-ceo-face-backlash-over-overseas-travel-amid-budget-cuts/news-story/084babdfe6cb2a15c5cb1d7c27ba08fb">The Gold Coast Bulletin reported</a>&nbsp;that the announcement has angered councillors who are dealing with budget cuts and staff redundancies.</p>



<p class="">Mayor Tate says he&#8217;ll meet with sporting officials to secure events for the 2032 Games and visit a modular housing factory.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Sunshine Coast</strong>&nbsp;Mayor Rosanna Natoli has declined to attend, citing local priorities.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Quilpie Shire Council</strong>&nbsp;has abandoned plans for a new aquatic centre after costs blew out to more than 36 million dollars.</p>



<p class="">Mayor Ben Hall says five years ago the project could have been built for around half that amount,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.indailyqld.com.au/news/just-in/2025/11/28/regional-council-abandons-36-million-aquatic-centre-plans">according to InDaily Queensland.</a></p>



<p class="">But instead, the council will now undertake remediation works to extend the life of the existing pool.</p>



<p class="">Dog-related complaints continue to pile up across Redlands Coast and Brisbane, with councils dealing with reports almost daily,&nbsp;<a href="https://redlandbaysidenews.com.au/dog-complaints-redlands-brisbane/">according to Redland Bayside News.</a></p>



<p class=""><strong>Redland City Council</strong>&nbsp;received 330 complaints about negative dog behaviour in the past financial year, while&nbsp;<strong>Brisbane City Council</strong>&nbsp;has dealt with more than 1500 animal incidents so far this financial year.</p>



<p class="">Strengthened penalties came into force in July 2024, including on-the-spot fines for failing to keep dogs under control.</p>



<p class="">Five dog breeds are now considered high risk and banned in Queensland.</p>



<p class=""><strong>North Burnett Regional Council</strong>&nbsp;has formalised&nbsp;<a href="https://northburnett.qld.gov.au/mayoral-media-release-25-november-2025/">a new partnership with Bundaberg Tourism</a>&nbsp;to boost tourism outcomes across the region.</p>



<p class="">The partnership aims to raise the profile of the North Burnett within the wider Bundaberg region brand.</p>



<p class="">Local tourism operators, accommodation providers and hospitality businesses can now access a 25 percent membership subsidy to join Bundaberg Tourism.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Tasmania</h2>



<p class="">A no-confidence motion against&nbsp;<strong>Derwent Valley</strong>&nbsp;Mayor Michelle Dracoulis has been defeated.</p>



<p class=""><a href="https://www.tasmaniancountry.com/newspaper/derwent-valley-gazette/councillors-attempted-no-confidence-motion-derwent-valley-mayor">Tasmanian Country reported</a>&nbsp;that Councillor Wayne Shoobridge’s motion failed to secure support from fellow councillors.</p>



<p class="">The move followed ongoing Code of Conduct complaints against the Mayor, which were previously dismissed by a hearing panel.</p>



<p class="">Mayor Dracoulis thanked councillors for their confidence and has confirmed she&#8217;ll run for re-election next year.</p>



<p class="">About 500 Westbury residents have signed a petition opposing&nbsp;<strong>Meander Valley Council</strong>&#8216;s plans to change their town hall.</p>



<p class=""><a href="https://www.examiner.com.au/story/9121372/westbury-residents-rally-against-town-hall-changes/">The Examiner reported that</a>&nbsp;community members say they&#8217;re not being heard after recently fighting off a prison proposal.</p>



<p class="">The Council is considering two options: refurbishing the hall into shared office space for $500,000, or building new offices and keeping the hall for $1.1 million.</p>



<p class="">Residents say the hall is critical for community groups like the local garden club, which has used it since the 1940s.</p>



<p class="">Mayor Wayne Johnston insists that public access to the hall was always intended to continue.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">South Australia</h2>



<p class=""><strong>Yankalilla District Council</strong>&nbsp;is&nbsp;<a href="https://www.yankalilla.sa.gov.au/news-and-events/latest-news/2025/rating-review-rebalancing-our-rating-system">reviewing its rating structure</a>&nbsp;to rebalance how rates are distributed across different property types.</p>



<p class="">It says the aim is to ensure fairness and long-term sustainability without increasing overall revenue.</p>



<p class="">The community is invited to participate through information sessions, online feedback, and direct contact with council staff across two phases of consultation.</p>



<p class="">The&nbsp;<strong>City of Mount Gambier</strong>&nbsp;is also&nbsp;<a href="https://www.mountgambier.sa.gov.au/news/special-council-meeting-rating-review">well advanced with its rating review.</a>&nbsp;A special meeting has heard from seven speakers, presenting their views to elected members on proposed changes, including concerns about the classification of short-stay accommodation.</p>



<p class="">Submissions are being reviewed by the Council, along with financial modelling, before it makes its decision on the rating structure.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="400" height="300" src="https://i0.wp.com/lgnewsroundup.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/Woodside-CFS-Mural-Taylr-Jay-2025-November-03_W400_H300.jpg?fit=400%2C300&amp;ssl=1" alt="" class="wp-image-6687" style="width:286px;height:auto" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/lgnewsroundup.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/Woodside-CFS-Mural-Taylr-Jay-2025-November-03_W400_H300.jpg?w=400&amp;ssl=1 400w, https://i0.wp.com/lgnewsroundup.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/Woodside-CFS-Mural-Taylr-Jay-2025-November-03_W400_H300.jpg?resize=300%2C225&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/lgnewsroundup.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/Woodside-CFS-Mural-Taylr-Jay-2025-November-03_W400_H300.jpg?resize=136%2C102&amp;ssl=1 136w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" /></figure>
</div>


<p class="">A new mural by South Australian artist Taylr Jay&nbsp;<a href="https://www.ahc.sa.gov.au/community/latest-news/work-underway-on-a-new-woodside-cfs-mural">is being painted on the Woodside CFS building</a>&nbsp;to celebrate the history and dedication of CFS volunteers in the&nbsp;<strong>Adelaide Hill</strong>s community.</p>



<p class="">The Council says the artwork has generated strong local interest and will serve as a colourful tribute to the volunteers who protect the region.</p>



<p class="">The&nbsp;<strong>City of Playford</strong>&nbsp;recently marked the 70th anniversary of the inauguration of the town of Elizabeth.</p>



<p class="">The milestone was acknowledged at a civic ceremony, conducted by Mayor Glenn Docherty.</p>



<p class="">The town was named after Queen Elizabeth II, and established as a satellite city of northern Adelaide to attract British migrants and support rapid post-war industrial growth.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Western Australia</h2>



<p class="">The&nbsp;<strong>City of Perth</strong>&nbsp;is in turmoil after its acting CEO Peta Mabbs resigned amid a dispute over a $125,000 workplace culture review ordered by new Lord Mayor Bruce Reynolds.</p>



<p class="">Ms Mabbs has declared the review unlawful and a poor use of ratepayer funds, saying no workplace culture issues had been identified in recent assessments.</p>



<p class=""><a href="https://www.abc.net.au/news/2025-11-28/city-of-perth-in-turmoil-as-acting-ceo-quits-amid-dispute/106074860">ABC News reported that</a>&nbsp;the review was pushed through with minimal notice and no debate, raising concerns among councillors who voted against it.</p>



<p class="">Local Government Minister Hannah Beazley has expressed concern and indicated she&#8217;s willing to intervene if necessary.</p>



<p class="">The saga has exposed deep divisions within the council just weeks after the new lord mayor took office.</p>



<p class="">The&nbsp;<strong>City of Stirling</strong>&nbsp;has shelved controversial plans to restrict free-roaming cats after admitting the proposal would likely be rejected by a state legislation review panel.</p>



<p class="">The proposed laws would have required permits for cat owners living within 200 metres of protected wildlife areas, affecting over 12,000 residents.</p>



<p class="">The city estimates roaming cats kill more than 360,000 native animals annually in the district.</p>



<p class=""><a href="https://www.perthnow.com.au/wa/perth/north/city-of-stirling-shelves-proposed-cat-containment-laws-over-legislative-hurdles-c-20742194">PerthNow reported that</a>&nbsp;State Government amendments to the Cat Act are expected next year, giving councils stronger powers to enforce responsible cat ownership.</p>



<p class=""><a href="https://www.ntnews.com.au/truecrimeaustralia/police-courts-nt/worksafe-has-charged-macdonnell-regional-council-over-the-drowning-death-of-a-2yo-boy/news-story/95853cd4ce18ac8d0a68ba79174c1d4a">The NT News reports</a>&nbsp;<strong>MacDonnell Regional Council</strong>&nbsp;in the Northern Territory has been charged after a two-year-old boy drowned at a Kintore early learning centre in December 2020.</p>



<p class="">Kumanjayi Jurrah was locked inside a swimming pool complex when carers took other children back inside.</p>



<p class="">NT WorkSafe alleges the council failed to ensure the child&#8217;s safety and maintain a safe work environment.</p>



<p class="">The council could face penalties up to $4.5 million if found guilty.</p>



<p class="">The case is listed for mention in court today.</p>



<p class="">The&nbsp;<strong>Shire of Harvey</strong>&nbsp;is investigating reclassification to city status as its population approaches 32,000.</p>



<p class="">The Council has approved a 15-thousand dollar budget for community consultation starting in February.</p>



<p class="">The change would see the shire president&#8217;s title upgraded to mayor.</p>



<p class="">A final report is expected in May 2026.</p>



<p class=""><em>Source: Ordinary Council Meeting Agenda, November 25, 2025 &#8211; Page 41-42</em></p>



<p class="">The&nbsp;<strong>Shire of Irwin</strong>&nbsp;has elected Cr Isabelle Scott&nbsp;<a href="https://irwin.wa.gov.au/media-release-new-shire-president/">as the new Shire President</a>&nbsp;and Cr Andrew Gillam as Deputy Shire President following recent council elections.</p>



<p class="">Cr Scott, a councillor since 2017, and Cr Gillam, serving since 2018, bring extensive experience and commitment to supporting the community&#8217;s growth and wellbeing.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Global Report</h2>



<p class="">NZ:</p>



<p class=""><strong>Westland Council</strong>&nbsp;Mayor Helen Lash has warned that uncertainty around local government reforms could trigger an exodus of council staff to Australia,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.odt.co.nz/regions/west-coast/jobs-council-staff-%E2%80%98safe%E2%80%99-mayor">according to the Otago Daily Times.</a></p>



<p class="">Under government proposals, three West Coast mayors will replace all seven regional councillors to form a territorial board.</p>



<p class="">Mayor Lash stressed that regional council staff jobs are secure and their expertise will be critical during the transition period.</p>



<p class="">She has also defended the need for council staffing levels, saying modern compliance requirements have made larger teams essential.</p>



<p class="">UK:</p>



<p class=""><strong>Royal Borough of Kensington and Chelsea Council</strong>&nbsp;has confirmed that historical data was copied and taken in cyber attacks targeting three London councils last week.</p>



<p class="">The council is now checking whether the stolen information includes personal or financial details of its 147,500 residents.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Westminster City Council</strong>&nbsp;and&nbsp;<strong>Hammersmith and Fulham Council</strong>&nbsp;were also affected due to joint IT arrangements, causing significant disruption to services and phone lines.</p>



<p class="">The Metropolitan Police have launched an investigation, with no arrests made yet.</p>



<p class="">Residents are being urged to be extra vigilant with calls, emails and text messages as the stolen data could end up in the public domain. Read more f<a href="https://www.notion.so/2b998cfa314a8105aae7fed299e38317?pvs=21">rom BBC News</a>&nbsp;and&nbsp;<a href="https://www.notion.so/2b998cfa314a819fa49ef527a54b33f1?pvs=21">The Guardian</a>.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Rugby Borough Council</strong>&nbsp;has broken ranks with other Warwickshire councils by supporting a single county-wide unitary authority.</p>



<p class="">Politicians from all three parties backed the move, opposing the north-south split favoured by the county&#8217;s four other district and borough councils.</p>



<p class="">And Rugby councillors want the new authority to be based in their town.</p>



<p class="">BBC News reports on the decision that came as a deadline for submissions to the government expired at the end of last week.</p>



<p class="">Andrew Crookham has been appointed as **Lincolnshire County Council&#8217;**s new chief executive, and he’s been given one immediate task: cut £1 million from the senior leadership team.</p>



<p class="">Council leader Sean Matthews says the savings target shouldn&#8217;t be difficult given the salaries involved,&nbsp;<a href="https://nz.news.yahoo.com/council-chief-told-save-1m-061857511.html">according to Yahoo News.</a></p>



<p class="">Mr Crookham is taking over from Debbie Barnes is retiring after nearly 20 years with the council.</p>



<p class="">CANADA:</p>



<p class=""><strong>Vancouver City Council</strong>&nbsp;has rejected a motion to lower the municipal voting age to 16,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.ctvnews.ca/vancouver/article/councillors-push-to-lower-vancouvers-municipal-voting-age-to-16-rejected/">according to CTV News.</a></p>



<p class="">The motion, brought forward by Councillor Pete Fry, was voted down, with those opposed saying the decision isn&#8217;t within the city&#8217;s authority and falls to the province.</p>



<p class="">The motion had noted that 16-year-olds can work, pay taxes, and drive, and that research shows a younger voting age fosters lifelong civic engagement.</p>



<p class="">Meanwhile, the council has&nbsp;<a href="https://www.ctvnews.ca/vancouver/article/vancouver-council-approves-zero-per-cent-property-tax-increase/">approved a zero per cent property tax increase</a>&nbsp;for the upcoming year, which means residents will see no change to their municipal property tax bills.</p>



<p class="">Details of likely cuts to services are yet to be disclosed.</p>



<p class="">US:</p>



<p class=""><strong>Sacramento City Council</strong>&nbsp;is moving to repeal a 76-year-old law that bans the sale of comic books depicting crime to minors<a href="https://www.latimes.com/world-nation/story/2025-11-23/sacramento-still-bans-sale-of-comic-books-to-kids-officials-want-to-change-that">, according to the LA Times.</a></p>



<p class="">The 1949 ordinance, which has never been enforced, was born out of mid-century fears that comics could inspire violence and delinquency.</p>



<p class="">Advocates say the repeal recognises the educational value of comics and protects against potential future censorship.</p>



<p class="">The committee also voted to establish an annual &#8220;Comic Book Week&#8221; in September. The measure now heads to the full council for approval.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://lgnewsroundup.com/overwhelming-demerger-vote-city-turmoil-and-concerning-misrepresentation-523/">Overwhelming demerger vote, city turmoil, and &#8220;concerning misrepresentation&#8221; &#8211; #523</a> appeared first on <a href="https://lgnewsroundup.com">Local Government News Roundup</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		<enclosure url="https://lgnewsroundup.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/Josh-Black-grab.mp3" length="624348" type="audio/mpeg" />

		<post-id xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">6685</post-id>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Newsfeed &#8211; Friday, 28/11/25</title>
		<link>https://lgnewsroundup.com/newsfeed-friday-28-11-25/?utm_source=rss&#038;utm_medium=rss&#038;utm_campaign=newsfeed-friday-28-11-25</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[LG News Roundup]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 22:07:23 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[QLD]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Victoria]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Western Australia]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://lgnewsroundup.com/?p=6674</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>New Shire of Irwin President and DeputyMelton push for rail line electrification&#8220;Indequate consultation&#8221; on transmission line: Upper Hunter ShireHorsham chooses mayor and deputyAvenel rally for rail safety upgradesAnger over Gold Coast mayor&#8217;s Winter Olympics trip WA: The&#160;Shire of Irwin&#160;has elected Cr Isabelle Scott&#160;as the new Shire President&#160;and Cr Andrew Gillam as Deputy Shire President following [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://lgnewsroundup.com/newsfeed-friday-28-11-25/">Newsfeed &#8211; Friday, 28/11/25</a> appeared first on <a href="https://lgnewsroundup.com">Local Government News Roundup</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p class=""><a href="#irwin">New Shire of Irwin President and Deputy</a><br><a href="#melton-rail">Melton push for rail line electrification</a><br><a href="#upper-hunter">&#8220;Indequate consultation&#8221; on transmission line: Upper Hunter Shire</a><br><a href="#horsham">Horsham chooses mayor and deputy</a><br><a href="#avenel">Avenel rally for rail safety upgrades</a><br><a href="#tate">Anger over Gold Coast mayor&#8217;s Winter Olympics trip</a></p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-medium is-resized"><img data-recalc-dims="1" loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="225" height="300" src="https://i0.wp.com/lgnewsroundup.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/Cr-Scott-768x1024-1.jpg?resize=225%2C300&#038;ssl=1" alt="" class="wp-image-6683" style="width:163px;height:auto" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/lgnewsroundup.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/Cr-Scott-768x1024-1.jpg?resize=225%2C300&amp;ssl=1 225w, https://i0.wp.com/lgnewsroundup.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/Cr-Scott-768x1024-1.jpg?w=768&amp;ssl=1 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 225px) 100vw, 225px" /></figure>
</div>


<p id="irwin" class="">WA: The&nbsp;<strong>Shire of Irwin</strong>&nbsp;has elected Cr Isabelle Scott&nbsp;<a href="https://irwin.wa.gov.au/media-release-new-shire-president/">as the new Shire President</a>&nbsp;and Cr Andrew Gillam as Deputy Shire President following recent council elections.</p>



<p class="">Cr Scott, a councillor since 2017, and Cr Gillam, serving since 2018, bring extensive experience and commitment to supporting the community&#8217;s growth and wellbeing.</p>



<p class=""></p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<p id="melton-rail" class="">VIC: <strong>Melton City Council</strong> is pushing the Victorian government to fast-track electrification of the Melton rail line.</p>



<p class=""><a href="https://meltonmoorabool.starweekly.com.au/news/council-urges-fast-track-for-melton-line/">The Star Weekly reported</a>&nbsp;that the council wants full funding committed, including new stations at Thornhill Park and Mount Atkinson.</p>



<p class="">The state government says rebuilding Sunshine Station is the first step toward electrification.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<p class="">The council is calling for a transparent timeline and delivery alongside the Sunshine Super Hub upgrade.</p>



<p id="upper-hunter" class="">NSW: <strong>Upper Hunter Shire Council</strong>&nbsp;has slammed the revised transmission line route for the New England Renewable Energy Zone,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.upperhunter.nsw.gov.au/News/Council-Meeting-Recap-24-November-2025">calling community consultation inadequate.</a></p>



<p class="">Mayor Maurice Collison says the route cuts through productive farmland and passes over 18 homes, contradicting EnergyCo&#8217;s own guidelines to avoid clusters of homes and agricultural land.</p>



<p class="">The Council will write to EnergyCo and NSW Energy Minister Penny Sharpe demanding investigation into using existing transmission corridors.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<p id="horsham" class="">VIC: <strong>Horsham Rural City Council</strong> has elected Cr Brian Klowss as mayor for the next year.<br>Cr Klowss has recently been acting in the mayoral role while Cr Ian Ross takes leave for health reasons.</p>



<p class="">Cr Rebecca Sluggett has been elected deputy mayor.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Frankston</strong> is the only council yet to elect <a href="https://lgnewsroundup.com/victorian-mayors/#google_vignette" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">a mayor for the forthcoming year</a>.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<p id="avenel" class="">VIC: The Avenel community is rallying on Saturday to demand $3.1 million from the Victorian Government for urgent rail safety upgrades. </p>



<p class="">A 10-year-old girl was seriously injured in April when hit by a freight train at the Bank Street crossing. </p>



<p class="">The community wants locking pedestrian gates, new crossings, and safety fencing along the rail line. </p>



<p class=""><strong>Strathbogie Shire</strong> Mayor Cr Scott Jeffery said Avenel was growing and it was essential local infrastructure kept pace.</p>



<p class="">Avenel Active says after four years of discussions, it&#8217;s time for action. </p>



<p class="">The State Government has been invited to attend the 11am rally at Harvest Home on Bank Street.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<p id="tate" class="">QLD: <strong>Gold Coast</strong>&nbsp;Mayor Tom Tate will bill ratepayers for a trip to Italy to carry the Winter Olympics torch in late January and February.</p>



<p class=""><a href="https://www.goldcoastbulletin.com.au/news/council/gold-coast-mayor-and-ceo-face-backlash-over-overseas-travel-amid-budget-cuts/news-story/084babdfe6cb2a15c5cb1d7c27ba08fb">The Gold Coast Bulletin reported</a>&nbsp;that the announcement has angered councillors who are dealing with budget cuts and staff redundancies.</p>



<p class="">Mayor Tate says he&#8217;ll meet with sporting officials to secure events for the 2032 Games and visit a modular housing factory.</p>



<p class=""><strong>Sunshine Coast</strong>&nbsp;Mayor Rosanna Natoli has declined to attend, citing local priorities.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://lgnewsroundup.com/newsfeed-friday-28-11-25/">Newsfeed &#8211; Friday, 28/11/25</a> appeared first on <a href="https://lgnewsroundup.com">Local Government News Roundup</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<post-id xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">6674</post-id>	</item>
	</channel>
</rss>